<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mirror of pure devotion: or, The discovery of hypocrisie Delivered in sixe severall sermons, in the Cathedrall Church of Chichester, by way of an exposition of the parable of the Pharises and the publican. By R.B. preacher of the word, at Chidham in the county of Sussex.</title>
            <author>Ball, Robert, fl. 1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13936</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13936)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 693:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mirror of pure devotion: or, The discovery of hypocrisie Delivered in sixe severall sermons, in the Cathedrall Church of Chichester, by way of an exposition of the parable of the Pharises and the publican. By R.B. preacher of the word, at Chidham in the county of Sussex.</title>
                  <author>Ball, Robert, fl. 1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 202, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt, for Richard Thrale dwelling at the Crosse keyes by Pauls gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.B. = Robert Ball.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MIRROR OF pure Devotion: <hi>OR,</hi> THE DISCOVERY of Hypocriſie. Delivered in ſixe ſeverall Sermons, in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> by way of an expoſition of the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Phariſee and the Publican.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. B.</hi> Preacher of the Word, at <hi>Chidham</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Corinth. 2. 14.</bibl> 
               <hi>The naturall man perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are fooliſhneſſe unto him: neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Verſe 15.</bibl> 
               <hi>But he that is ſpirituall diſcerneth all things: yet he himſelfe is judged of no man.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Aut appare quodes, aut eſto quod appares.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Legatt,</hi> for <hi>Richard Thrale,</hi> dwelling at the <hi>Croſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyes</hi> by <hi>Pauls</hi> gate. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, RIGHT worthy, and his much honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Mecaenas <hi>William Drury</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, one of the Gentlemen of His Majeſties moſt honorable Privy Chamber, all increaſe of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, with endleſſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of eternall happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Iámque opus exegi.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Ovid</hi> concludes his Poetry, ſo may I begin my Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I am at length delivered of that birth, which mine unfained zeale to Gods glory, mine humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to his Church, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective
<pb facs="tcp:13936:3"/> obſervance unto your worſhip, have beene this many yeeres conceiving in mee; and whereof neither the barrenneſſe of the wombe, nor the hardneſſe of the travell, nor the unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the midwife, nor the rough handling of ſome ill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Goſsips, could (being ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly aſsiſted by the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) make mee miſcarry. How timely and comely the fruit may be, the predominant End I ayme at (the glory of God) gives mee ſufficient boldneſſe; and the two ſubordinates (my ſervice in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to the Church, in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to your worſhip) give mee ſufficient incouragement to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to the eye of the world: wherein if it ſhall finde but chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh entertainment, I ſhall not marvell. I know ſufficiently the world cannot brooke its nature:
<pb facs="tcp:13936:3"/> the diſcovery of an hypocrite or a Phariſee deſerves no leſſe then a Crucifige at the worlds hands, that is ſo full fraught with both. But I know againe there be ſome in the world, that are called out of the world, becauſe they are not of the world, that will bid my child good wellcome; ſuch as leane neither to the right hand of Schiſme, nor the left of hereſie, but worſhip the Father in ſpirit and in truth: amongſt which ſmall number your worſhip is well noted and approoved, for ſincere and eminent. To theſe therefore under your worſhips protection, I deſire to commend my firſt fruit with Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> bleſsing, in his <hi>1. Epiſt. 4. 4.</hi> Little babe, thou art of God, and therefore thou ſhalt overcome the world, for greater is he that is in thee, then he that is in the world. So
<pb facs="tcp:13936:4"/> he, that is in thee, keepe thee in him; and he, that hath overcome the world for thee, defend thee from the world, and from the men of the world, whoſe teeth are ſpeares and arrowes, and their tongue a ſharpe ſword. And the God of peace tread Sathan under thy feet ſhortly. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips, in all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and true-hearted ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance, alwayes to bee commanded in the Lord Ieſus. RO: BALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13936:4"/>
            <head>THE MIRROR OF PVRE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOTION: OR, THE DISCOVERIE OF HYPOCRISIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
               <q>Alſo hee ſpake this parable unto certaine, which truſted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they were juſt <hi>(or righteous)</hi> and deſpiſed others.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, (having in the former part of this Chapter, moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully exhorted, and perſwaded his diſciples to the undeniable and never-ceaſing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of Faith, by a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance traduced from an importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13936:5"/> widdow and almoſt inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Iudge,) beginnes now to draw them to humility of heart in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſinne by a parable of two men, a Publican become the ſonne of God, and a Phariſee the ſervant of Mammon. Better is a penitent offender, then a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous juſticiarie: for, in that the one humbleth himſelfe, hee is no longer an offender, <hi>Every valley ſhall bee exalted;</hi> and in that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſwelleth with an imaginarie opinion of ſelfe-conceited purity he is no longer righteous; <hi>Every mountaine and hill ſhall bee brought lowe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa 40. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It was long ſince rung in the eares of curioſitie, preſuming to <note place="margin">Eraſ. Ap.</note> out-reach humane capacitie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day pluckes downe high things and lifes up baſe things. Our God is in heaven (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid)</hi> and doth whatſoever pleaſeth him. As God judgeth not after the outward appearance like unto man, ſo his proceedings are quite
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13936:5"/> contrary to the courſe of the world; they grow from a little to more, from a baſe meane there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts a mighty matter. The world it ſelfe was made of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: The eternall Word it ſelfe was compared to a ſlender graine of muſtard ſeede: Chriſt himſelfe came out of <hi>Galile</hi> a contemptible citie: and heere a penitent Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can is juſtified rather then a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Phariſee. But the courſe of the world is altogether retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade; like <hi>Ahaz</hi> his diall, it runs backeward, from greater to leſſe, from oſtentation to confuſion. <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazar</hi> in his princely royaltie at ſupper; but in the hand-writing upon the wall, he and his Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy numbred, weighed, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to others. So here, a full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwollen Phariſee, all glorious in the ſight of his owne eies, but moſt odious and abominable in the ſight of God. The Saints prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (it ſeemes) comes neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt; It is the Lord that judgeth, whoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13936:6"/> eies are puritie, whoſe eares jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, <note place="margin">Bern.</note> whoſe word veritie, whoſe hand equitie, and whoſe daies e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie. <hi>Invocat pauper, et exaudit Dominus; flet miſerabilis, et flectitur miſericors; agnoſcit Publicanus, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcit et Chriſtus.</hi> The poore man cals upon, and the Lord liſtens un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; the miſerable man mournes, and the mercifull God is mooved; the ſinner confeſſes, and the Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our forgives. <hi>Confeſſio ſalus anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amb.</note> 
               <hi>diſſipatrix vitiorum, reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix virtutum. oppugnatrix Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num; quid plura? obſtruit os infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, aperis portas Paradiſi.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſins is the ſaving health of ſoules, the diſperſing of vice, the repaire of vertue, the overture of the Divel: What ſhall I ſay more (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine)</hi>? it ſtoppeth <note place="margin">Aug.</note> the very gulfe of hell, and openeth unto us the everlaſting doores of Heaven.</p>
            <p>The whole Parable depends upon theſe foure Generalls. The Preface: The Parable it ſelfe: The Event: And the Application.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13936:6"/>
            <p>The Preface is ſet downe, in this ninth verſe:</p>
            <p>9. <hi>Alſo he ſpake this parable to certaine that truſted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they were juſt, (or</hi> righteous) <hi>and deſpiſed others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parable it ſelfe, in the 10, 11, 12, and 13. verſes.</p>
            <p>10. <hi>Two men went up into the Temple to pray: the one a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee. and the other a Publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>11. <hi>The Phariſee ſtood, and prayed with himſelfe thus, God I thanke thee, that I am not as other men are, extortioners, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, adulterers, or even as that publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>12. <hi>I faſt twice in the weeke, I give tithes of all that I poſſeſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>13. <hi>But the Publican ſtanding afarre off, would not lift up ſo much as his eies to heaven: but ſmote his breſt ſaying; O God, be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The event, in the former part of the 14. verſe.</p>
            <p>14. <hi>I tell you this man departed to his houſe juſtified rather then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13936:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Application in the latter part of the ſame verſe:</p>
            <p>For every one that exalteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhall be brought low, and he that humbleth himſelfe ſhall be exalted.</p>
            <p>The Preface admits of a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Quaere.</hi> The firſt is, what may be the meaning or ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word Parable? The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is, what may be the reaſon, why our Saviour ſo often in the Goſpel ſpake unto the people by parables? The third and laſt is, what may be the occaſion, why he ſpake and delivered this parable? which appeares by the Text, to be a diſcoverie of three groſſe corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in certaine of his auditours. The firſt was a preſumptuous ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence by reaſon of a fond conceit of merit in their owne workes; They truſted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. That preſumptuous ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence begat an arrogant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of inherent righteouſneſſe; that they were juſt. And that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13936:7"/> conceit of inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe hatched the third genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the viper, That they vilified and deſpiſed others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo hee ſpake a parable to certaine that truſted in themſelves, that they were juſt (or</hi> Righteous) <hi>and deſpiſed others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt, <hi>Quaene</hi> leades us to the Etymologie, or ſignification of the word Parable; which is taken either in the worſer, or in the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part.</p>
            <p>When it is taken in the worſer part, it ſignifies a by-word, a word of reproach, or a fable. As the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites <note place="margin">Pſal. 44. 14.</note> in the Pſalme, <hi>Poſuisti nos (Domine) in parabolam.</hi> Thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ade us, O Lord, a parable, or a proverbe, or a by-word amongſt the heathen. So the Lord by his ſervant <hi>Moſes</hi> threatens a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious <note place="margin">Deut 28.</note> people, that They ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a wonder, a proverbe, and a by-word amongſt all nations. So that holy man <hi>Ioh,</hi> complaines in <note place="margin">Iob 17. 6.</note> the heate of his miſerie, that God had made him a proverbe, or a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13936:8"/> of the people. And ſo not onely <hi>David</hi> the type, but the <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 12.</note> ſonne of <hi>David</hi> the ſubſtance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, that he became a parable, or a proverbe unto the people, and that the very drunkards made ſongs upon him.</p>
            <p>When it is taken in the better part, it ſignifies, either ſome grave and weighty matter, ſuch as <hi>David</hi> uttered upon his Harpe. Or elſe <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 4.</note> ſome ſhort and ſweete ſentence, ſuch as <hi>Salomon</hi> delivers in his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbes.</hi> Or elſe ſome darke, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, or figurative ſpeech, when the truth is wrapped up in a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or a compariſon as in a riddle. Thus the Lord commanded the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> to ſpeake a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Ezek. 24. 3.</note> unto the rebellious houſe, and ſay; <hi>Prepare a pot, and put water in it, &amp;c.</hi> Ezechiel 24. 3. Vnder which ſhaddow, is repreſented both the ſinne and the puniſhment of impenitent <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And in this ſence our Saviour tels his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. <note place="margin">Matth. 13.</note> Matth. 13. <hi>That hee ſpake unto the people by parables, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13936:8"/> they might not ſee, and hearing they might not heare, neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the Prophecy of Iſaiah might bee fulfilled upon them.</hi> And this muſt needs be the moſt genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and proper ſignification of the word parable, from the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>aſſimulare:</hi> being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe (as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> notes) but <hi>Sermo ſimilitudinarius, qui aliud dicit, aliud ſignificat;</hi> A comparative or an Enigmaticall kinde of ſpeech, ſpeaking one thing; and ſignifying another: as it plainly appeares, not onely in this, but in all the parables of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Quaere</hi> leades us to the reaſon, why our Saviour ſo often in the Goſpel ſpake unto the people by parables? which I find to be threefold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the accompliſhment of Scripture-prophecies. This was our Saviours owne reaſon. Matth. 13. before mentioned, therefore doe I ſpeake to them in parables, that the prophecy of Iſaiah might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13936:9"/> bee fulfilled upon them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for the confirmation of other Scripture-prophecies; to give us to underſtand, that Chriſt ſpake not onely by the ſame ſpirit, but with the very mouth, and phraſe, and language of all the holy Prophets, that ever were ſince the world beganne; whoſe writings are full of compariſons, ſimilitudes, and parables.</p>
            <p>Thirſtly, and laſtly: That the myſteries of the Kingdome might be hidden from the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of this world, and onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto babes in Chriſt: that to them onely might bee given to know the ſecrets of the Kingdome, but to others in parables. And therefore the holy Scripture is apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compared by Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o flumen in que ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kt, &amp; Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> na tet</hi> Ep. ad Leand.</note> a flood, wherein the Lambe may wade, and the Elephant ſwim. Though parables are darke myſteries unto the proude and skornefull, yet they are made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert and plaine unto the humble and meeke. Our bleſſed Saviour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13936:9"/> in his infinite wiſedome conceived it to bee the quainteſt, and moſt profitable kind of teaching, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the ſimple people by ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and parables: which being once truly underſtood, doe migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily delight the underſtanding, helpe the memory, move the will, captivate the affections, caſt downe the imaginations, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high thing, that is exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the knowledge of God, and bring into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>How ſtrangely did <hi>Nathans</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable winde it ſelfe ſecretly into the heart of <hi>David,</hi> convincing him ſo modeſtly, and ſo ſtrongly too, that his owne mouth condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to be that man of blood the parable intimated? Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.</note> caught the Iewes in the very ſame trap by putting a queſtion unto them in the parable of the Vineyard, and ungracious huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen. <hi>When the Lord of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 21. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Vineyard ſhall come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what ſhall hee doe to theſe husbandmen.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13936:10"/> They themſelves replye, and plead themſelves guilty in the very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer following. Hee will cruelly deſtroy thoſe wicked men, and let out his Vineyard to others. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon our Saviour inferres moſt bitterly, but moſt juſtly: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay unto you, the kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Seneca</hi> held the uſe of para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <note place="margin">Epiſt 59.</note> ſo neceſſary to wade through the ſhallow ſtudie of humanitie, that hee calls them, <hi>Imbecillitatis nostrae adminicula,</hi> props and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of our weakeneſſe; how much more needfull are theſe bladders to beare us up in the maine Ocean of Divinitie; they may be ſomething windy, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding profitable: <hi>Diſcentem et audientem in rem praeſentem addu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca):</hi> Plaine ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, familiar examples, and homely compariſons doe force more doctrine into vulgar appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, then ſubtill reaſons, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid arguments, or accurate diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. When every Mechanicke is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13936:10"/> argued withall in his owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, every Tradeſman in his owne occupation, and every coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Swaine in the naturall dialect of his owne barbariſme; it muſt needs informe the underſtanding, reforme the will, and ſo mightily edifie the whole man, that it wil e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven pierce through to the dividing aſunder of the ſoule and of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, of the joynts and of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; nay it will dive into the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſecret thoughts and intentions of the heart.</p>
            <p>For ſay, I beſeech you; Is not the parable of the hidden treaſure abundantly able, to convince the Vſurer in particular? The parable of the fruitleſſe figge-tree, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Gardiner? The houſe built upon the ſand, the Maſon? The ſtrong man armed, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier? The loſt groat, the Widow? And the loſt ſheep, the Shepheard? and each, or all of theſe aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly able to inſtruct all? What plough-man is there in the world ſo ſtupid, but, when hee reads the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13936:11"/> parable of the Sower, <hi>Luke</hi> 8. both propounded, and expounded unto him by our bleſſed Saviour, is able to reade unto himſelfe a Lecture of ſound Divinitie, and medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te with himſelfe thus:</p>
            <p>That as himſelfe goes forth into the field to ſowe his ſeede; ſo the Sonne of man came once perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the world to ſow the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall ſeed of his ſacred Word, in the hearts of beleevers; and to this very day hath left behind him Miniſteriall Seeds-men (the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Goſpel) to dreſſe, and dung, and to manure his field, and ſow his ſeede. As hee himſelfe cannot poſſibly ſcatter his ſeede ſo choicely, but ſome will of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fall by the hie-way ſide, and ſo either be troden under foote of men, or devoured of the fowles of the Ayre: ſome will fall amongſt the ſtones, and then no ſooner it ſprings up, but withers away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for want of moiſture: ſome will fall amongſt thornes, and ſo the thornes ſpring up with it and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13936:11"/> choake it: It is but the fourth part that falls upon good ground, that ſprings up, and beares fruit; ſome thirty, ſome ſixty, ſome an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold.</p>
            <p>So the Preachers of the Goſpel cannot poſſibly ſcatter the good ſeed of the Word ſo choicely, but doe what they can, ſome will fall by the hie-way ſide that is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt careleſſe, drouſie, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent hearers, and then it is either trodden under foote of men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and vilified, or elſe devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the fowles of the ayre; that is, the Devill and his inſtruments ſteale it out of the hearts of the hearers, leſt they ſhould beleeve and bee ſaved: ſome will fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſtones, hard and flinty hearts, where the Word for a time may be received with joy, but for want of roote the people beleeve for a time, and in the time of temptation they fall away: ſome will fall amongſt thornes; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and licentious hearers, in whom the cares of the world, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13936:12"/> of riches, and the luſts of other things doe ſo choake the Word, that it becomes unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: It is but the fourth part, or ſcarce that, which fals upon good ground, that with an honeſt and good heart, heare the Word, and keepe it, and bring forth fruite with patience. Vpon which due, and ſerious meditation, he cannot chooſe but bring the Application of the parable home to himſelfe, himſelfe then being in the very act of ſowing. When hee ſees three parts of every handfull of temporall ſeed he ſowes, in danger of miſcarrying, ſome falling by the hieway-ſide, ſome amongſt ſtones, and ſome amongſt thornes, hee cannot chooſe but grieve, and much lament it: oh, how ought it then to perplexe his ſoule, and yearne his very bowels to conſider the moſt lamentable hardneſſe, and intolerable barrenneſſe of his owne heart, that receives not the moſt precious ſeed of the Word of God, with any reaſonable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13936:12"/> cheerefulneſſe, muchleſſe returnes it with any tolerable fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. See what lumpes of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity lye hid and buryed under the very clods of the earth; what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Lectures of Divine litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may bee read in the very field at plough; ſo profitable are thoſe doctrines in Scripture, that are couched by our bleſſed Saviour under Similies and Parables.</p>
            <p>In what a lamentable and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous condition then is the ſtupid Papiſt in forbidding, and the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent carnall Goſpeller in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to reade the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, both building their <hi>Babel</hi> upon this ſandy foundation, That they are darke myſteries, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure parables. Whereupon the Papiſts ſome of them forbid the reading of the Scriptures to the Laytie, as a thing moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and pernitious for them; being (as they affirme) the roote and ſeminary of all ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, the mother and the nurſe of all hereſie and faction. Chriſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13936:13"/> commands us to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 19.</note> for eternall happineſſe; they countermand it with a <hi>Noli me tangere</hi> for feare of hereſie. The Spirit of Chriſt exhorts us to try the ſpirits whether they bee of God; becauſe many falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are come into the world: theſe ſpirits forbid the common people the very touch-ſtone of tryall. The ſpirit of truth adviſeth <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3. 16.</note> us to give the Word of God all poſſible entertainement; not to lodge with us as a ſtranger for a night, but to dwell in us plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as a continuall In-mate: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is profitable to teach, to improove, to correct, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct in righteouſneſſe. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of errour counſels to banniſh it quite out of our coaſts, and in ſtead thereof to bring in ignorance for the mother of devotion. The one tels us, it is the peoples inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; the other tels us, it is the peoples deſtruction. The one tels us, it makes the man of God perfect and abſolute; the other
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13936:13"/> tels us, it makes him hereticall and diſſolute. And ſo wee may ſafely conclude with Reverend <hi>Wickeliffe</hi> and that <hi>Iewell</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> To condemne the Word of God of hereſie, is no better then to make God himſelfe an hereticke.</p>
            <p>But the very truth is (beloved) the Scriptures make men here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, no otherwiſe then the Sun makes men blind. As nothing is cleerer then the Sunne, and yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing harder to be looked into for the weakeneſſe of our ſight: So nothing more manifeſt then the Scriptures in themſelves, and yet nothing more obſcure then myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries therein contained, for that the naturall man perceives not the things of God. Say then, (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) Is light darkeneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe darkeneſſe comprehends it not? Is ſweet ſowre, becauſe ſome men taſte it not? no more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenly are the Scriptures obſcure becauſe ſome men underſtand them not. Wee deny not then a kinde of obſcuritie to bee in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13936:14"/> Scriptures, both in regard of the profunditie of the particular points, and of our diſabilitie to conceive them: but the manner of the deliverie is not obſcure in it ſelfe, but familiar and eaſie to them that have their ſenſes prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the holy Ghoſt to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, and uſe the meanes that God hath ordained for that end.</p>
            <p>Let the wary Proteſtant then, that would carefully avoid the Papiſts ginne, ſoundly diſtinguiſh of theſe three. The myſteries de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered: the manner of the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: and the indiſpoſition of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver. The things themſelves are myſteries: therefore ſecret, and involved in divers difficulties. The indiſpoſition of our underſtanding not onely darke, but darkeneſſe it <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 8.</note> ſelfe (therefore were they never ſo cleere wee could not poſſibly underſtand them, till we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned. But for the manner of the delivery, in it ſelfe it is apert and patent: if any where darke, it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13936:14"/> is accidentally and from without. And therefore S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes <note place="margin">In Ep: ad Coloſſ.</note> none from the comfortable uſe of the Scriptures, but makes generall Proclamation to all ſorts of people: <hi>Audite quotquot eſt is mundani, &amp;c.</hi> Hearken all ye men of the world that have wives and children, how <hi>S. Paul</hi> the Apoſtle of Chriſt, commandes you to read the Scriptures, and that not ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or perfunctorily, but with great diligence. Yea, the ſame Father is ſo eager upon the point, that he doth, as it were, force and thruſt the Bible into the peoples hands. Take the Bible into your hands (ſaith he) in your houſes at home. So likewiſe <hi>S. Ierome,</hi> moſt <note place="margin">Jerome.</note> gravely and divinely, urges upon the ſame place of Scripture, that Lay-men ought to have the Word of God, not only ſufficiently, but abundantly; whereby they may bee able to teach, and to counſell others.</p>
            <p>But bee it granted, that ſome places of Scripture are obſcure and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13936:15"/> darke: it were but a fallacy <hi>à ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum quid ad ſimpliciter</hi> (as the Logicians call it) to argue from thence, that the Scriptures are full of darkneſſe: becauſe ſome are difficult to ſome, therefore all are dangerous to all ſorts of vulgars? The Prophet <hi>David</hi> reades a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Lecture to us, and tels us, <hi>That the Word of God is a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne unto our feete, and a light un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our pathes.</hi> And therefore Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> buildes upon a ſure foundation. <hi>Omnia clara &amp; plana</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Gen. Hom. 29.</note> 
               <hi>ſunt in Scripturis Divinis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quaecunque neceſſaria ſunt, manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſunt.</hi> All things are cleare and plaine in the Holy Scriptures, whatſoever things are neceſſary for us, are alſo manifeſted unto us. Whereupon <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus</hi> makes an other Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as hee is quoted by the ſame <hi>Chryſoſtome. Audite qui eſt is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In 2 Theſ. Hom. 3.</note> 
               <hi>longè, auditè qui prope; nullis caela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt verbum.</hi> Hearken yee that be farre off, hearken yee that bee neere, the Word of God is hid
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13936:15"/> from no man. As <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Iſraelites. It is neither in heaven, <note place="margin">Deut. 30.</note> that wee need hire any to climbe for it; nor yet beyond the Seas, that we need get any travell for it; but the Word of God is in our owne mouthes, and in our owne hearts to doe it. <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt communis, omnibus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Clem A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. orat. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hort ad gentes.</note> 
               <hi>illuceſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it, nullis in verbo Cymm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rius.</hi> As God, ſo his Word, is that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Light, that inlightneth every man that comes into this world, in it there is no darkeneſſe at all. So <hi>Irenaeus: Scripturae in aperto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. 45.</note> 
               <hi>ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> The Scriptures are plain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and without doubtfulneſſe, and may bee read indifferently of any. So Saint <hi>Ierome:</hi> The Lord hath ſpoken by his Goſpell, not that a few ſhould underſtand him, but that all. For certainely (beloved) the Spirit of God is a free Spirit, bound neither to the ſharpeneſſe of our wit, nor to the deepeneſſe of our learning: for many times the ſimple and illiterate man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing illuminated ſees more then the Scribe, or the great diſputer
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13936:16"/> of this world. According to that clauſe of our Saviours prayer. Matth. 11. <hi>I thanke thee O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, for that thou haſt hidden theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them unto Babes.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Epiphanius</hi> divinely: <hi>Solis Spiritus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Sancti filiis facilis eſt Scriptura.</hi> The Scriptures are plaine and cleere onely to the children of the holy Ghoſt. The Spirit breatheth where it liſteth, without which wee can neither live, nor move, nor have any ſpirituall being; we are meere dead men, and therefore muſt needs be blind men. But to thoſe that are illuminated, whether lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or unlearned, there ariſeth up light in darkeneſſe. There is food of all ſorts, for all ſorts of people; <hi>So Fulgentius: In Scripturis Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Serm. de con.</note> 
               <hi>abundat, &amp; quod robuſtus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edat, &amp; quod parvulus ſugat.</hi> In the Word of God there is plenty ſufficient, ſtrong meate for men, milke for Babes. It is the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groomes Wine-cellar, wherein he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13936:16"/> feaſteth and comforteth his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Spouſe, with Flagons, and Apples, and delicates of all ſorts; whereof ſhee hath free welcome and liberty, <hi>bibere &amp; inebriari,</hi> to drinke and to bee ſatisfied, and to drinke, and to bee more then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</p>
            <p>So farre are the reverend Fathers (you ſee) from fathering the abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of hereſie, and ſchiſme upon the ſacred Scriptures; that they rather indeed proclaime them to be the ſevere ſtep-mother, or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſſe of ſuch Cockatrices in the egge. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> confeſſes ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that the onely cauſe of the Valentinian hereſie was, <hi>Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum Dei ignorantia,</hi> the peoples blindneſſe and ignorance of the Scriptures. So Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> concerning the errour of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees in his time, <hi>Manichaei &amp;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ad Heb. hom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>omnes haereſes decipiunt ſimplices.</hi> The Manichees and all hereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es deceive the ſimple. But if our mindes bee illuminated by often reading and hearing of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13936:17"/> we may be able to diſcerne both good and evill. So likewiſe <hi>Theophylact: Illis, qui ſcrutantur Divinas Scripturas, nihil poteſt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere:</hi> nothing can deceive them that diligently ſearch the Holy Scriptures, it is the candle where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the theife is diſcovered. So the ancient of dayes himſelfe unto the Sadduces. Yee erre (not becauſe <note place="margin">Math. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yee know, but) becauſe yee know not the Scriptures. For hereſies, or ſchiſmes ariſe not from the Scriptures themſelves, or any dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them; but from the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and pravity that is in mans underſtanding; they are rather diſcovered and ſuppreſſed by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Should I tell you, that a blind man may better avoyd dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers then he that ſeeth: Or that a naked man in the middeſt of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies may better acquit himſelfe then he that is compleately armed: Or that the full fed I picure is nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſtarving, then the miſerable captive, that is debarred all kinde of ſuſtenance; you might well
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13936:17"/> thinke I were mad: So (certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) it argues no leſſe frenzie and in compoſſibilitie of minde, to broach ſuch unreaſonable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely doctrines.</p>
            <p>But to winde up this controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in one word. It were an eaſie matter (me thinkes) to catch the adverſary in his owne gin, if wee did urge him to nominate, what manner of perſons hee thinkes meete in his owne conſcience, to be exempted from the reading of the Scriptures? Hee cannot ſay, old men, for ſhame; they are the very ſtaffe and comfort of their age. It was the ſweete <hi>amabaeum,</hi> and burden to <hi>Davids</hi> ſong when hee was aged. In Gods Word will <note place="margin">Pſal 58. 10.</note> I rejoyce; in the Lords Word will I comfort me. Not young men for pitty: they are the onely curbe to reſtraine the heate and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their tameleſſe youth: for wherewithall ſhall a young man cleanſe his waies, but by ruling <note place="margin">Pſal 119. 9.</note> himſelfe according to Gods word? Surely the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> thought
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13936:18"/> it the beſt breeding hee could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly beſtow upon his ſonne <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15.</note> to bring him up in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Scriptures from a child. Not women or maidens, for the frailty of their ſex ſake: for how then ſhould ſuch weake and brittle veſſels, become ſtrong in <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 10.</note> the Lord, and in the power of his might, as they are commanded? It is enough for that Apoſtate <hi>Iulian</hi> to quarrell with the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for that their women were skilfull in the Scriptures: But ſure I am, good old <hi>Nazsanzen</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the never-dying fame of his ſiſter <hi>Gorgonia,</hi> by a funerall Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for that ſhe was skillful both in the Old and New Teſtament: and reverend <hi>Ierome,</hi> of Lady <hi>Paula</hi> by an Epitaph, for that all the may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens about her, were forced daily to learne the Scriptures. Not poore men, for Gods ſake: the chiefeſt almes they can aske, or receive, is the free paſſage of the Goſpel. Whereupon our Saviour ſpeakes <note place="margin">Matt. 11.</note> it, not only for their warrant, but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13936:18"/> their commendation: That the poore receive the Goſpel, with all alacritie and cheerefulneſſe. So it hath pleaſed our gracious God, in all ages, by his infinite wiſedome and mercy, to make choice of the poore of this world (as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh) that they ſhould be rich in faith; and that by often hearing and reading of the Scriptures. Not infidels or hereticks, for charity ſake; It is the onely ordinary meanes of their converſion: And therefore it was permitted that Queene <hi>Candaces</hi> Chamberlaine, being an infidell, might reade the <note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> Scriptures without controlment. And S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> confeſſeth, that himſelfe, being inclined to the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <note place="margin">Conf. lib. 8. c. 12.</note> of the Manichees, by reading the Scriptures was converted. If then neither old nor young; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents nor children; men nor boyes; women nor maydens; learned nor unlearned; rich nor poore; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks nor infidells, may lawfully be exempted from the reading of the Scriptures; we may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13936:19"/> thoſe hypocrites, that our Saviours woe directly points at: That take away the key of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <note place="margin">Matt. 23.</note> that ſhut up the kingdome of heaven before men; and neither enter themſelves, nor ſuffer others to enter in. Alas, (ſaith <hi>Irenaeus) Hoc non eſt ſanantium &amp; vivificanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 3. c. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſed magis gravantium &amp; augen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ignorantiam:</hi> This is not the part of them that would heale and give life; but rather of them that augment the burden, and increaſe ignorance.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt <hi>Quaere</hi> yet behind, moſt proper and pertinent to the text of all, is, What might be the occaſion, why our bleſſed Saviour ſpake and delivered this Parable?</p>
            <p>The occaſion wee muſt needs conceive could not bee ſlight, that induced the wiſedome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to propound a ſpeciall para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. It was the diſcoverie of a whole neaſt of ſectaries, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Text. Certaine (it ſeemes) there were,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13936:19"/> that would bee ſingular above the reſt, the common gap to all kinde of hypocriſie, and confuſion in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: for marke (I beſeech you) the growth of their faction; The maine roote of all, was the roote of all miſchiefe, pride. From thence ſprang up the ranke blade of ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence; out of an arrogant proud ſpirit, attributing every good thing in themſelves, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: they truſted in themſelves. From thence ſhot forth the full care of preſumption; an arrogant conceit of inherent righteouſneſſe, that they were juſt. And then their harveſt grew on ſo faſt, that their too forward fruit were not onely, <hi>albae ad meſſem,</hi> but even <hi>ſiccae ad ignem,</hi> ripe for the hooke, but dry for the fire; their arrogant ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity pearched them up, upon ſo high a ſtraine of boaſting of their owne eminencie, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and deſpiſed others. All which Circumſtances being duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the truly zealous, and rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> humble auditor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13936:20"/> that there was too juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for our Saviour to propound, and us to expound this Parable.</p>
            <p>Selfe confidence? what a wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den head of folly, a broken ſtaffe, and a rotten poſt of preſumption is it? which hath not only ſought to make Angels, but men equall to God himſelfe. But whom ſhe hath ſo proudly lifted up; ſhee hath likewiſe moſt miſerably caſt downe: What miſchiefes indeed hath ſhee not done? Shee hath caſt <hi>Lucifer</hi> out of Heaven; <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe; overthrowne the tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Babell, and brought in the firſt confuſion of languages; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated <hi>Goliah</hi> with diſhonour, and ſlue <hi>Nicanor</hi> with reproach; finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Antiochus</hi> his Empire, and drowned <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the red Sea; cauſed <hi>Senacherib</hi> to be ſlaine by the hands of his owne ſonnes in the temple, and <hi>Herod</hi> by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell in his Parliament; <hi>Abſolom</hi> to periſh by his owne locks, and <hi>Haman</hi> to totter upon his own gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. Broken reeds are not ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13936:20"/> dangerous to him that leaneth, nor ſlippery Ice to him that runneth, nor the beautie of an harlot to him that luſteth, as ſelfe-confidence is pernicious to him that imbraceth it. Broken reeds may wound the fleſh, ſlippery Ice procure deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate fallings, the beautie of an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot bring ſhame before, and begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry behind: but ſelfe-confidence ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away God from the ſoule, the ſoule from the body, the body from immortalitie; It fadeth when it flouriſheth, it is not when it ſeemes to be, it falles and never ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againe. Man, truſting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, (ſaith <hi>Gregory)</hi> is falne like <note place="margin">Gregor.</note> a dead leafe from the Cedar in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, and is blowne away with the tempeſt of temptation, and winde of vanitie. As <hi>Sauls</hi> coate of armour was an hinderance to <hi>David,</hi> that his hands could not warre, nor his fingers fight; as <hi>Peter</hi> walking upon the Sea, was in hazard of drowning: ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is man being left unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nothing but deſolation; His
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13936:21"/> birth corruption, his life tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, his death confuſion: In his birth miſerable, in his life culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in his death of himſelfe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: His knowledge imperfect, his life uncertain, his mind chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and he himſelfe nothing but fragilitie. And therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the point with Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine: Confidentia in ſcipſo eſt lubri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca ſpes, incerta victoria, impoſſibilis liberatio:</hi> It is a flattering and fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel hope for a man to thinke he is ſafe and inviolable amongſt the infinite increaſings, and daily nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhings of ſinne; It muſt needs be a doubtfull and uncertaine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory for a man to fight amidſt his enemies ambuſhment; and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible delivery to be invironed on every ſide with fire, and not to bee ſcorched. And ſuch was the deſperate condition of theſe Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the firſt ſtep or degree of their affected ſingularity, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence: they truſted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>To this woodden head of theirs,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13936:21"/> ſelfe-confidence, they muſt needs annexe the brazen face of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, a whoriſh fore-head that cannot bluſh, preſumption of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. They are abſolutely perfect in their owne eyes, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable with God, equall with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, ſuperiour to their brethren. Whereas alas, mans righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (ſaith <hi>Gregory)</hi> being weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Gregor.</note> in the ballance with Gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is found to bee nothing but unrighteouſneſſe: and that the more vile in the examination of the upright Iudge, by how much the more glorious it ſeemed in the partiall eſtimation of the owner thereof. A candle that burnes bright in the darke, is dimmed at noone day. <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> his maskers coates were thought all gold over night, in the Chamber of preſence by torch light, but found nothing but Wheat-ſtraw the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the wardrobe. <hi>Leah, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> elder daughter, was ſaid to be browne and bleare-eyed in regard of beautifull <hi>Rachell</hi> the younger.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13936:22"/> When wee have done all that wee can, the very Prince of Prophets tels us, wee are but unprofitable ſervants; And if we will be tryed by a brace of inferiours, that ſpake by the ſame ſpirit with him; the one tels us, that all our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is as filthy as a menſtrous ragge; the other, that wee our ſelves are altogether lighter then vanity it ſelfe. Without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the merit of finnefull man can bee nothing but miſery, his knowledge errour, his worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, his invention deceivea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, his profeſſion colorable, his will abhominable: And as the Moone is ecclipſed being removed from the irradiation of the Sunne: As Rivers dry up, not watered from their fountaines: As Trees wither, not moyſtened from the earth: ſo the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifie in the old and rotten roote of nature, if they be not tranſplanted and implanted into the ſtocke of grace. If in that we live, it is not of our ſelves, how can that bee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13936:22"/> ours that we doe poſſeſſe? A moſt groſſe kinde of folly, I bluſh not to call it meere ſtupidity, for a man to acknowledge the benefit of his life from another, and yet to aſcribe the ornament of his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to himſelfe. In God we live, and moove, and have our being: what then can any man have, that hee hath not received? And why then ſhuld any man boaſt as if he had not received it? Goodneſſe (ſaith <hi>Bernard)</hi> is the Vineyard of <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> the juſt Man; or rather a juſt Man is a good Vineyard; whoſe Vine is his vertue; whoſe branch, acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whoſe Wine, the teſtimony of a good conſcience; whoſe Winepreſſe, is the tongue of praiſe; whoſe godly teares of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, are the Grapes of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; whoſe pruner, is the Preacher; and the Lord of this Vineyard, is the God of Heaven. Such then was the deſperate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of theſe ſectaries in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſtep, or degree of their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſingularity, an arrogant and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13936:23"/> preſumptuous conceit of inherent righteouſneſſe: That they were juſt.</p>
            <p>To their woodden head of ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence, and brazen face of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, to make up a perfect monſter of imperfection, they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe the iron heart of crueltie, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then the neather mill-ſtone; and farre more apt to ſting then the biting nettle, Contempt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I am not like that Publican, (ſaith the fore-man of their Iury in this Parable, that brings in the verdict for all the reſt) ſpying a mote of infirmitie in his brothers eye, but not diſcerning the beame of impietie in his owne; ſtraining at every Gnat hee meets in the ſtreet, but leaping over every Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel that lyes at his own threſhold; nothing is ſweet that fits not his taſte, but all things unſavoury that ſeed not his humour; barking at the Stars like a Dog in the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, and hiſſing in a corner like a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; conſuming the next mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber like a Canker, and gnawing an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13936:23"/> iſſue in the wombe of his mother like a Viper: <hi>viſcera impiorum cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delia.</hi> Contempt of our brethren? It is the unkinde diſſolution of the whole frame of nature, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth chiefely in ſocietie. It is a rottenneſſe in the marrow, a fire in the body, a fury in the ſoule, the ruſt of a good conſcience, the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of charitie, the enemy of peace, the breach of unitie, the mother of miſchiefe, the nurſe of contention, the daughter of pride that is never barren; It is a frenzy infecting the head, vexing the ſpirit, moleſting the heart; It filles the head with wicked inventions, they ſleepe not (ſaith <hi>David)</hi> till they have done miſchiefe; The minde with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed thought, <hi>Iuaas</hi> ſought op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to betray Chriſt; The heart with bloody revenge, <hi>Cains</hi> countenance was caſt downe, he roſe up and maſſacred his brother. Contempt of our brethren? It is the ſeed of ſedition, the brand of a reprobate, a Locuſt of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit, the ſonne of thoſe Gyants
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13936:24"/> Anach, and Anakim, a murdering ſpirit, and a ſpirituall murderer; ſo Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> expreſſely: He that hateth his brother is a man-ſlayer. And ſuch likewiſe was the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table condition of theſe ſectaries in the third and laſt ſtep or degree of their affected ſingularitie Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of their owne eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and contempt of others.</p>
            <p>As therefore our bleſſed Saviour hath upon theſe grounds propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; ſo proceed we in his name, and by the aſſiſtance of his ſpirit, to expound this parable. Wherein wee may obſerve as in a glaſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative the perfect character of an hypocrite; whoſe genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie hath many generations. Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of the Serpent, begate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence; concupiſcence, ſinne; ſinne, ill cuſtome; ill cuſtome, blind devotion; blind devotion, wilfull ignorance; wilfull ignorance, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; hypocriſie, vaine-glory; vaine-glory, ſelfe-love; ſelfe-love, ſelfe-confidence; ſelfe-confidence, preſumption of righteouſneſſe; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13936:24"/> of righteouſneſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of others; contempt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, a Phariſee: And a Phariſee begate two twins, hypocrits both: the one a diſſembler with his God, the other a deceiver of his brother: and both of them either bearing private grudges in their hearts as <hi>Cain</hi> to <hi>Abel,</hi> or elſe open reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in their mouthes as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> till they both fall into the pit that they digge for others.</p>
            <p>I have now brought you to the threſhold of the parable, where for this time I muſt needs leave you: the text I named, and the time I am bound to obey, have granted commiſſion to proceed no further.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:25"/>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13936:25"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke 18. 10.</bibl>
               <q>Two men went up into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pray: the one a Phariſee, and the other a Publican.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE have already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched the Preface in the former Verſe, which lead our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations to a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Quaere.</hi> The firſt, to the Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie, or ſignification of the word Parable. The ſecond, to the reaſon, why our Saviour ſo often in the Goſpel ſpake unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13936:26"/> by parables? The third and laſt, to the ſpeciall occaſion, that induced him to propound this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>Proceede wee now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by Gods aſſiſtance and your chriſtian patience, to enter upon the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it ſelfe. Which being a glaſſe repreſentative, of the perfect cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of an Hypocrite: I ſhall bee ſo farre from perſonall invectives in the proſecution thereof, that I ſhall deſire all in generall, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their faces in it. Not (as the common courſe of the world is) for a man to glance over the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon his brother, as if the doctrine delivered concerned not himſelfe: Or, like S. <hi>Iames</hi> his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, to take ſo ſlight a notice, that preſently hee forgets it at the turning of the backe: but with a ſerious and particular application to the conſcience, and with a full purpoſe and reſolution of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For (though I confeſſe) the drift of the parable aymes moſt punctually at the Hereticke and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13936:26"/> Schiſmaticke, in whom the ocean of hypocriſie ſwels to a full Sea: yet, before we have done with it, wee ſhall finde it will reach us all, and ſpare none: for as much as he that is ſoundeſt at the heart, may at one time or other (if hee flatter not himſelfe too much) diſcover in himſelfe ſome dregs of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, ſome ſpice of the Phariſee. Let every one then in the feare of God, apply the parable onely to himſelfe, as ingenuouſly taxing his owne conſcience, as <hi>Nathan</hi> did <hi>David,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Tu es homo,</hi> Thou art the man our Saviour now taxes, and the Preacher now ſpeakes to. That ſo every one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to mend one, God in his mercy may mend all. And upon this good reſolution, by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Author, we may venter upon the Parable.</p>
            <p>Two men went up into the Temple to pray: the one was a Phariſce, and the other a Publican.</p>
            <p>That great Divell incarnate, Hypocriſie in devotion, is heere
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13936:27"/> diſcovered unto us by our bleſſed Saviour, by a parable of two men, as like in outward ſhew, that it is very hard to diſcerne the one from the other; but as different in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſubſtance, as light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Their behaviour is expreſſed in the words of this Text, joyntly together; then ſeverally and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, in the verſes following. At firſt ſight a man would thinke all were well. Here are firſt, <hi>Duo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines,</hi> two men; good company. Here is ſecondly, <hi>aſcenſus in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum,</hi> they walke, and they talke, and they converſe together, and they goe up into the Temple to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; a good poſture. Here is thirdly, <hi>Devotio,</hi> a ſeeming ſtrong devotion; They goe up into the Temple to pray; a good exerciſe. But alas, heere is the leaven that ſowres all, and ſwels all, the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Phariſees: <hi>The one was a Phariſee, and the other a Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Duo homines,</hi> two men? why good company, and once a rarity
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13936:27"/> to bee found upon the face of the earth. Without all queſtion, ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie is both commendable and comfortable, by the principles of nature and grace to: for though <hi>unum &amp; bonum cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtuntur,</hi> by our mecaphyſicall diſcipline; yet hee that ſoares but one degree higher ſhall finde, that the moſt perfect unitie is beſt pleaſed to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a Trinitie: No doubt, to ſignifie, that as there can bee no true ſocietie without an unitie; ſo there can bee no perfect unitie without a Societie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Went theſe two men up into the Temple? they could not have trod a fayrer path. A journey that <hi>David</hi> undertooke with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacritie and cheerefulneſſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when hee went up into the Temple with companie; the more the merrier. I was glad (ſaith h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) when they ſaid unto me, <hi>Wee will goe into the houſe of the Lord.</hi> It is a good ſight to ſee men go by twoes into the Temple; but a farre more bleſſed, to ſee them flocke by tens,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13936:28"/> and hundreds, and thouſands: As (bleſſed bee God) in this, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Congregations in this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Went theſe two men up into the Temple to pray? they could not have gone with a better reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, nor performed a better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe. Had they gone but ſingly up into a private chamber, or a cloſet to pray, and beene ſtill; it had beene (no queſtion) an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſacrifice of righteouſneſſe: Devotion, bee it never ſo private, if it be hearty, ſhall never returne emptie without a bleſſing. It is like <hi>Davids</hi> Tree planted by the <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> waters ſide, whoſe leafe never wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but ſtill brings forth fruit in due ſeaſon; whatſoever it doth it ſhall proſper. It is a fruitfull Vine, continually bearing cluſters of ripe grapes; whoſe roote, is chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; whoſe ſtocke, faith; whoſe top, hope; whoſe ſpreading twigges are laden with fruite, the workes of mercie; and whoſe flouriſhing bloſſomes, are the wholeſome
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13936:28"/> wordes of wiſedome.</p>
            <p>As the morning Starre in the midſt of a cloud; As the Moone <note place="margin">Eccle. 50.</note> when it is at full; As the Sun ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon the Temple of the moſt high; As a bright raine-bow in faire clouds; As the flower of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſpring; As Lillies by the rivers of water; As fire and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe in the Cenſer; As a veſſell of maſſie gold, beſet with all manner of precious ſtones; As a faire O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live tree that is fruitfull; As a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe tree that growes up to the clouds; And as the fat that is taken from the Peace-offering; ſo is the <note place="margin">I am. 5. 16.</note> prayer of the righteous man if it be fervent. It is paled in like the garden of Eden with everlaſting mercies, when the beſt of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices are layed waſte and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; It floates like <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke upon the waters of affliction, when the beſt of our thoughts are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed and periſh; It buds and bloomes like <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, and brings forth ripe Almonds, when the beſt of our works remaine dry
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13936:29"/> and wither; This one ſheafe ſtands upright, and this one ſtarre ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles, when the reſt of the hile fall flat upon the ground, and all wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Comets are quite obſcured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abigals</hi> bottles of Wine, and frayles of Raiſons were never ſo welcome to hungry <hi>David</hi> in the wilderneſſe of Parran; Nor the ſhadie Iuniper tree ſo delectable to the Prophet in the parching Sun; Nor <hi>Iacobs</hi> fat Kid, ſo acceptable to his fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſaac</hi> in his ſickneſſe; Nor the ſight of young <hi>Benjamin</hi> ſo pretious to his brother <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> when he was the chiefe Governor of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court in <hi>Egypt;</hi> Nor the Wals of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſo deare unto the Iewes, that kiſſed them at their returne from captivity: as zealous and hearty prayer is unſpeakeably comfortable to the ſoule of a diſtreſled ſinner. It fils the mouth with laughter, and the heart with gladneſſe: It gives light to them that ſit in darkneſſe, and life to them that ſit in the ſhaddow of death: it is <hi>Damoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13936:29"/> flagellum, animae ſubſidium, Deo ſacrificium.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> A ſcourge to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, a prop to the Soule, a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God, which God cannot deſpiſe: It is the continuall feaſt of a pined conſcience; the onely ſolace in a Sea of ſorrowes: <hi>(Call upon me in the time of trouble,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>ſo will I heare thee and thou ſhalt praiſe mee.)</hi> It is the very <note place="margin">Lodovicus Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euſ.</note> ſtation of the ſoule in the preſence of God, and the ſtation of God in the preſence of the ſoule; God lookes upon her with the Eye of mercy, and ſhe glances upon God with the eye of humility. What ſhall I ſay more? It is the food of the Soule; the quinteſcence of all ſpirituall comfort; the obtaining of all the graces and favours of the great King of Heaven; the raviſhing ſeale of that interchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able kiſſe of peace, betwixt the Bridegroome and the Bride; that ſpirituall Sabbath, wherein the Creator himſelfe deſires to reſt; that Lodge in the forreſt of <hi>Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> wherein the true <hi>Salomon</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13936:30"/> himſelfe, and enjoyes his delights with the ſonnes of men. It is milke for Babes, ſtrong meat for men, proviſion for the travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, an haven to the mariner, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to the militant, and glory to the triumphant. It is phyſicke to the ſicke, joy to the afflicted, ſtrength to the weake. It amends the bad, it confirmes the good, it comforts all. It is the Gate of Heaven, the firſt fruits of future glory, the heavenly Manna of all raviſhing ſweetneſſe, and the <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> Ladder that reaches from<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Earth to Heaven, whereby the Angels aſcend and deſcend, to carry up our petitions, and to bring downe Gods bleſſings.</p>
            <p>If ſuch then bee the power and efficacy of private devotion, how much more powerfull is the ſtrength of publike prayer? If the bubling of one ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit-pipe be ſo harmonious in the eares of God, how acceptable is the noyſe of many waters? If the one bee ſo potent, the other muſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13936:30"/> needs bee omnipotent; (If wee may bee ſo bold to uſe the phraſe of <hi>Alstedius) Eſt quaedam omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Syſtem. theol.</note> 
               <hi>precum,</hi> (ſaith hee) There is ſuch a kind of majeſty and omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency in publike prayer, that it raiſes the dead, it overcomes Angels, it caſts out devils, and (which is more wonderfull then all the reſt) it ſeemes to maſter and over-maſter God himſelfe; inabling the feeble Chriſtian, to wreſtle with his Maker, as <hi>Iacob</hi> with the Angell, with a <hi>non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittam,</hi> I will not let thee go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> without a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Thus farre then the Parable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds well: that there were two men, it was good company; that they went up into the Temple, it was a better poſture; that they went up into the Temple to pray, it, was the beſt exerciſe, <hi>That houſe ſhall bee called the houſe of prayer.</hi> But heere is that which turnes <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> quite backewards, makes the company uncomfortable, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture prepoſterous, and the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13936:31"/> moſt execrable, the one was a Phariſee, and the other a Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. That two men ſhould be of two mindes; the ſame in ſhew, but different in ſubſtance; come up into the Temple, and to pray too, and not with one accord in one place; this turnes our honey into gall, the waters of <hi>Meribah</hi> into the waters of <hi>Marah: The one was a Phariſee, and the other a Publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mention is often made in the Goſpell of Phariſes, to the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reproach of their life, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere reprehenſion of their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe; who either with the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe traditions of men, or the fruitleſſe objections of the Law, ever went about to intangle our Saviour in his ſpeech. <hi>But in vaine is the net layed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of the winged.</hi> A buſie <note place="margin">Prov.</note> ſect it ſeemes they were: for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when they went with him into the Temple, they lift up their heeles againſt him, like deceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able hypocrites; or elſe in the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13936:31"/> judgement-hall they ſpend their mouthes againſt him with a <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifige,</hi> crucifie him, like murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous homicides. Their lippes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve much knowledge of the Law, and yet the poyſon of aſpes is under their throate. The morall precepts are written in their Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacteries with a thorne to pricke their Anckles, and yet their feete moſt ſwift to ſhed blood. They ſit in the Chaire of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and yet reſiſt the Lords anointed with <hi>Corah.</hi> They bind heavy burdens upon the ſhoulders of other men, and yet they touch them not with their owne fingers.</p>
            <p>Greater enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, which is his glory and our Salvation, were there none than Phariſees. Not <hi>Pilate</hi> the judge with his halting opinion, and luke-warme religion. Not <hi>Caia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> the high Prieſt with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward malice, and outward holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Not <hi>Iudas</hi> the traitor with his kiſſing lip, and killing heart. Not the vulgar route and rabble
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13936:32"/> of the Iewes clamorouſly acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Barrabas</hi> the malefactor, and deſpightfully condemning Ieſus the innocent. And yet forſooth none ſo pure, none ſo holy in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion as a Phariſee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hujuſmodi venandi fallacias ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Orig. in Math.</note> 
               <hi>Satanas, ſub titulo ſanctitatis agere inſidias.</hi> It is Satans uſuall ſleight of hunting, by a ſhew of holmeſſe to intrap the ſimple. Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees in the eye of the world re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for mirrors, ſhrined for Saints, canonized for halfe gods: and yet for all this glittering pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended piety, in the judgement of Chriſt and his witneſſes, true Reedes ſhaken with the Winde, painted Sepulchres, Wolves in ſheepes cloathings, Scribes and Phariſees, hypocrites, woe be unto them.</p>
            <p>Thus hath Satan juggled from the beginning, and continually changed himſelfe into an Angell of light. <hi>Ciceroes</hi> Rhetorician, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> Polititian, and <hi>Homers</hi> Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler are not ſo lively painted in their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13936:32"/> colours, as here a Phariſee, in his due and true conditions, his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit conſcience being diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the vizard of hypocriſie, ſemblable to religious ſanctimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, pluckt from his face of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency. For though he be a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus</hi> of many ſhapes, and variable changes; (and never a change from worſe to better; (for <hi>deſinit eſſe melior, qui deſinit eſſe bonus,)</hi> hee that ceaſes to be good in the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, is farre from proceeding to better in the Comparative:) Yet heere like the Moone, hee may be ſeene at full: he is totally Ecclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with his God; hee is waxing and waining with the world; He is almoſt at laſt quarter, darkened and obſcured in ſoule to himſelfe. In that, an hypocrite, drawing neere unto God with his lips, but farre from him in his heart; In the other, a heretike, ſaying, Loe heere is Chriſt, and there is Chriſt, we know not where; And in this an Atheiſt, neither hot nor cold, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a name to be alive, but indeed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13936:33"/> is dead. And as the Maſter tooke the firſt draught of this hypocrite for former; ſo the Scholler conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues it for latter times, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 2. Where he telles us, that men ſhall be lovers of their own ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, curſed ſpeakers, diſobedient to parents, unthankfull, unholy, without na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection, truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, intemperate, fierce, deſpiſers of them that are good, traytors, heady, high-minded, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of pleaſure, more then lovers of God. This for the Phariſee, now for the Publican.</p>
            <p>Of whom (yopu may well ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) that much cannot bee ſaid, having ſo little to ſay for himſelfe, onely he craves the benefit of his booke: <hi>Miſerere mei Domine,</hi> ſo farre hee reads Clarke-like, <hi>O God bee mercifull to mee a ſinner.</hi> And therefore for charitie ſake, we may plead thus much for him: As the Phariſee ſaid of himſelfe, that hee was not as this Publican; ſo may wee juſtly ſay of this Publican,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13936:33"/> that hee was not as the Phariſee; whatſoever the Phariſee was, hee was not; and whatſoever the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee was not, that was he; in the ſight of God, in the ſight of man, and in the ſight of his owne eyes. A man of no publike fame, but publike infamy; His very name diſcovers both his nature and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice too; a poore Publican, a tribute gatherer, an under-cuſtomer, an officer of the baſeſt accompt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Iewes; both by reaſon they were ſervants to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, whoſe yoake they could not indure, and alſo grinding ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acters of more then their due for their owne advantage. This pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like contempt of others made him at length ſeeme odious in his own eyes: for <hi>peccat &amp; publicat</hi> (though not in <hi>Senecaes</hi> ſenſe) he ſinnes, and he publiſhes his ſinne, not to <note place="margin">Sen.</note> his glory, but to his ſhame; not to the erection of his head, but to the confuſion of his face; and when he was ſmalleſt and vileſt in his owne eyes, he was then in greateſt repute
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13936:34"/> and eſtimation in the ſight of God; as it ſhall appeare (God willing) more at large hereafter. In the meane time wee ſee the parable turnes upon theſe two hinges; A proud boaſter, and an humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour; A preſumptuous juſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and a penitent offender; An ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant hypocrite, and a dejected ſinner. <hi>Theſe two men went up into the Temple to pray; the one a Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, and the other a Publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a generall reſemblance is there betwixt hollow hypocriſie, and truly religious ſanctitie, that the Church may too juſtly lament and complaine, that her children are blacke like unto coales, no man <note place="margin">Lam. 4.</note> is able to diſcerne them when hee meets them in the ſtreets; and that the great Citie of God is become like an harlot. This generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance is ſet down in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of this Parable, by foure ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial repreſentations; wherein pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hypocriſie, and naked ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie may ſeeme at firſt both alike, or rather hypocriſie, to carry the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13936:34"/> fairer ſhew. The firſt is, the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the perſons, <hi>duo homines,</hi> two men, the Phariſee and the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, one for one; and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly greater, is the multitude of hypocrites.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the old world and dayes of <hi>Noah</hi> with his two faces, the one looking to the world periſhing, the other to the poſterity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but eight perſons were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <note place="margin">Gen 8. 1 King. 22. 6.</note> in the Arke. But one <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiah</hi> againſt foure hundred falſe Prophets. <hi>Elias</hi> complaines that he is left alone, and not five good men to bee found in thoſe great and famous Citties of <hi>Pentapolis.</hi> But onely three brethren in that mighty flow of idolatry, and Empire of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi> One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thouſands of Iſraelites entred into the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour cured ten Leapers, and but one returned thankefull. And therefore he foretold, that in theſe laſt dayes many falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe and deceive many;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13936:35"/> 
               <hi>For ſtraight is the Gate, and narrow is the way, that leadeth unto life, and few there bee that finde it.</hi> The Church of God is a little flocke: a ſmall ſhip for <hi>Simon</hi> to launch out into the deepe. <hi>Paphnutius</hi> ſtood againſt the whole Councell of Nice; <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> againſt the Councell of Conſtance; <hi>Luther</hi> alone forſooke his Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter; and theſe three men, (by the helpe of their God,) in their times prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Generality then, and the greater number, can be no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the true Church. <hi>Auxenſius</hi> made a proude challenge to the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine: Nos habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus conſenſum &amp; concentum ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centorum Epiſcoporum;</hi> Wee have the conſent and harmony of ſixe hundred Biſhops: and yet he was an Arrian.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond reſemblance is in externall forme, and outward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, wherein they are ſtill both alike; they both aſcend and goe up. As well the idolatrous Iew to <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> to worſhip <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:13936:35"/> calves, as the true Iſraelite to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to worſhip the living <note place="margin">Iob 2.</note> God: Vpon a certain day, the children of God came and ſtood before him, and Satan came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them too: They like Prieſts cloathed with righteouſneſſe, and Saints ſinging with joyfulneſſe; but he, either like a ſubtill Serpent ſeeking whom hee may deceive; as he did <hi>Eve,</hi> in the Garden; <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> in the High Prieſts hall; and <hi>Iudas</hi> at the Paſſeover: Or elſe, as a roaring Lyon into the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; an accuſer of his brethren; as he entered into <hi>Cain</hi> the fratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide; and <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate: Or elſe a red Dragon, for the triall of their faith and patience; as unto <hi>Iob,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> when the meſſenger of Satan was ſent to buffet him. Thus <hi>Cain</hi> goes to the Altar to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, as well as <hi>Abel. Iudas</hi> will have a finger in Chriſts diſh, as well as <hi>Iohn.</hi> The Phariſee carries a countenance of holineſſe, a grace of godlineſſe, and a ſhew of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, more then doth the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13936:36"/> and yet they both goe up; here is yet ſmall difference.</p>
            <p>The third reſemblance is, One place, the Temple receives them both. Where God will have his Church, the divell will bee ſure to have his chappel. As in the world there is heate and cold; night and day; hill and valley. As in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Arts there is oppoſition of Sciences, Sophiſtrie and probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, rage and reaſon, affirmation and negation, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con:</hi> So in Gods Church militant, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious faction will be ſure to couch under the ſame roofe, with true devotion; diſguiſed hypocriſie, with naked piety; and ſhameles vanitie, with ſimple veritie. Where the painefull husband-man ſowes pure ſeede; there the envious man will ſcatter tares. Where <hi>Paul</hi> plants the grafts of grace and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; there <hi>Alexander</hi> the Copper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, inſerts his imps of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and impietie. Where <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peter</hi> preaches converſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; there <hi>Simon Magus</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13936:36"/> conjuration by the Divell. <hi>Dagon,</hi> the Idoll and folly of the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> and the Arke of God, the glory and felicitie of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, were ſometime both in one houſe. <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke harboured as well ravenous wolves, as tame and ſimple creatures; The Lambe, and the Woolfe; the Raven, and the Dove; the Adder, and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vt lilium inter ſpinas, ſic Eccleſia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bern. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>Dei bonis atque malis permiſta eſt.</hi> As a lilly growes up betweene two thornes; ſo the outward viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church is a mixt Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good and bad. As in all gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, grow as well weedes as hearbes: As upon all trees, as well blaſſe as bloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome: As in all rivers, as well frogges as fiſh: So <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael; Magus</hi> and <hi>Philip;</hi> Publican and Phariſee, goe up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Temple together.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to them both, is, One end and purpoſe, in generall to pray. Some worſhip the hoſt of heaven,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13936:37"/> calling the Sunne <hi>Iſis,</hi> and the Moone <hi>Oſiris;</hi> as the Ethnicke and Pagan. Some an Idoll, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the glory of the Creator, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſimilitude of the creature; a calfe that eateth hay; as the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domite and Gentile: But in vaine are theſe men, and their hope is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them that go downe into the pit. Some truſt in their owne merits, not Gods mercie; in their owne workes, not Chriſts wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe: In the invocation of the Mother a ſinner, and not the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Sonne the onely Saviour; robbing him of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, whereof hee is ſo juſtly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that he will not impart it to another.</p>
            <p>But the humble Publican, and truely penitent, layes his prayer a ſteepe in a flood of teares; throughly ſpiced with a broken and contrite heart, ground to powder betwixt the two mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones of faith and hope; truſting in God as in a mercifull Father, leſt hee ſhould deſpaire; and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13936:37"/> to dread him as a moſt juſt Iudge, leſt hee ſhould preſume, as did this Phariſee.</p>
            <p>It is obſerved by <hi>S. Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> upon the 1. of <hi>Matt:</hi> That as Chriſt made foure wonderfull followers of himſelf: Of a ſimple fiſherman, a learned Paſtor of the Church, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> Of a Perſecutor in <hi>Iewry,</hi> a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher and Doctor of the Gentiles, <hi>Paul:</hi> Of a Publican, ſitting at the receit of Cuſtome, a chiefe Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt; <hi>Matthew:</hi> And of an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious theife upon the Croſſe, a glorious Saint in Paradiſe. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the falſe Prophets would make themſelves wonderfull fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt too; creeping up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the flocke in ſheeps clothing of innocency, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inwardly they are ravening wolves ful of hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>Thus is the Church of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Cribbe, a cradle for Chriſt, and a manger for the Aſſe. <hi>Mendacium imitatur verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jerome.</note> Hypocriſie will have <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſmall voice, though the rough hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> hereſie, <hi>Iudas</hi> his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13936:38"/> kiſſe in the lippe like a diſciple, but a curſe in the heart like a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell: And a Phariſee will bee puft up like a bladder, both in words and countenance. The flies <hi>Cantharides</hi> breede (they ſay) in the ſweeteſt roſes. The Palmer worme neaſteth in the faireſt Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar. The flatterer crouches to a man of the beſt nature. And hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hypocriſie will be an inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable companion, to religious ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie. Lucifer is fallen like a ſtar, and hath gotten him a new kinde of policie, under the name of Chriſt to deceive the ſimple. Some things are, and yet not ſeene, as the ſpirit of a man: Some things both are, and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, as the body of a man; Some things neither are, nor ſeene, as the thoughts of a man: And ſome things ſeeme, and are not, as the ſhadow of a man; a perfect emblem of phariſaicall ſimulation. <hi>Rachel</hi> was never ſo cunning for her father <hi>Laban,</hi> in ſitting upon his idols hid in the litter: Nor <hi>Mic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> ſo crafty for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13936:38"/> 
               <hi>Saul,</hi> in the conveyance of <hi>David:</hi> Nor <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſo pregnant an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Phariſee is to halt with his God, and to gloze with his brother; hee ſeem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to goe up neighbourly into the Temple with the one, and to pray devoutly to the Other.</p>
            <p>The laſt worke then, that wee have to doe for the Concluſion of this exerciſe, is to ſettle, and quiet the conſcience in ſo turbulent a Sex of diſtracted devotion. That two men went ſociably in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany together, thou likeſt it well. That their ſociety led them ſo faire a way, to goe up into the Temple together, thou likeſt it better. That their journey tended to ſo good an end, to goe up into the Temple to pray, it raviſhes thy contemplation. But that the one ſhould be a Phariſee, and the other a Publican; that there ſhould hee ſuch Hereſie and Schiſme in the Church, ſuch fractions and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the publike body; and ſuch deceiveable hypocriſie in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13936:39"/> members; this (I dare ſay) troubles the conſcience much, and cooles thy devotion more.</p>
            <p>And why ſo? Knowſt thou not that <hi>Rebecka</hi> had two twinnes, <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coh</hi> and <hi>Eſau;</hi> the one a veſſel or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to honor, the other to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour? why theſe were the <hi>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> homines,</hi> wee now treate of: and therefore ſhee a lively type and Emblem of the Church militant. <hi>Semen unum, diverſi concepti; uterus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>unus, diverſi nati;</hi> The ſeed one, the conception divers; the wombe one, the birth divers: And why ſhould not the Church then take as patiently, as <hi>Rebecka</hi> did, the ſtrugling of her twinnes?</p>
            <p>Knoweſt thou not againe? that our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. compares the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which is his Church militant, unto an husbandman that ſowed good ſeede in his field; but while men ſlept, the envious man came and ſowed tares: which, when the ſervants perceived, they by all meanes counſell their Maſter to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13936:39"/> weede them up. But the Maſter in his wiſedome would not grant it, leſt they ſhould plucke up the good corne, with the cares; and therefore hee reſolves upon a <hi>ſinite utroſque croſcere;</hi> let both grow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether untill the harveſt. To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſuch weeders amongſt the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinthians;</hi> the Apoſtle was faine to propoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an <hi>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t hareſes eſſe;</hi> and tell them plainely, that there was; and muſt bee diviſions, and he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſies, even amongſt them, the true Church of God; that they which are approoved might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee knowne. There muſt be hereſie to try thy faith; there muſt bee ſchiſme to try thy judgement; there muſt be furie to try thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; there muſt be frenzie to try thy wiſedome; there muſt be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie to try thy ſoundneſſe. Shouldeſt thou fall from thy God to an Idol with the hereticke; where is thy faith? Shouldſt thou rend thy ſelfe from his Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Schiſmaticke; where is thy judgement? Shouldeſt thou
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13936:40"/> play faſt and looſe with both, like an Hypocrite; where i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid ſi totus mundus adora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> 
               <hi>Saranam?</hi> It is <hi>Tertullians</hi> caſe: what though the whole world ſhould forſake God, and ſerve the Devill, ſhall God therefore looſe his ſervice of thee? <hi>Si Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopus, ſi diaconus, ſi vidus, ſi virgo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſi doctor, ſi etiam Martyr lapſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regula fuerit, numid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hareſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem videbuntur obtinere to</hi> ſaith the ſame father. What if a Biſhop; a Deacon, a Widdow, a Virgin, a Doctor or maſter in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> nay, what if a Martyr of Chriſt Ieſus ſhall f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll from the rule and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of faith, ſhall hereſie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore ſeeme to obtaine the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the truth? or ſhall the truth ſhrinke from the proud face of hereſie? what if two men goe up into the Temple together; the one a Phariſee and the other a Publican? <hi>Non ex perſonis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus fidem, ſed ex fide perſonas:</hi> we doe not approove of the faith of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13936:40"/> Chriſt by the perſons of men, but the perſons of men by the faith of Chriſt. Or what if two men goe up into the Temple by ſucceſſion? <hi>Non habet haereditatem Potri, qui fidem Petri non habet:</hi> Hee cannot inherit <hi>Peters</hi> chaire, that doth not inherit <hi>Peters</hi> faith. The Iewes could boaſt themſelves to bee of the ſeede of faithfull <hi>Abraham:</hi> but our Saviour tels them they are no better then the ſeminary of their father the Devill. After S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> departure grievous Wolves were to enter in, not ſparing the flocke. The deſolation of abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation wa to ſit in the holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and Antichriſt himſelfe, that man of ſinne in the Temple of God. <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Ezecki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Ieroboam David,</hi> and now the Turke is crept into the foure Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchall ſeates; <hi>Alexandri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och. Et in Romana eccleſia ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dent Scribae &amp; Phariſei.</hi> The Scribes and Phariſees ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> his chaire at Rome too. They are not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13936:41"/> all Iewes (it ſeemes) that dwell at Ieruſalem, nor all Iſrael that are of Iſrael, nor all of the Church that are in the Church; nor all of the Temple that goe into the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pray. The hedge-ſparrow many times hatches the yong Cuckooe; and the Hen ſits upon the egge of the yong Cockatrice; and frogs come into <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Chamber; Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, Nullifidians and Atheiſts, Anabaptiſts, and Adiaphoriſts, and all come up into the Temple to pray.</p>
            <p>And what of all this? <hi>Eſto tu rectus,</hi> onely be thou upright and all ſhall worke together for the beſt to thee that loveſt God, and art effectually called according to his purpoſe. <hi>Mali tecum eſſe poſſunt in area, in horreo nunquam erunt.</hi> Well may evill men be with thee in the ſeed-furrow, but they ſhall never bee with thee in the barne. They are yet in the furrow and tillage, as thoſe that to day are bad, but to morrow may be good,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13936:41"/> as was this Publican; and they which preſume to day that they are perfect, to morrow may bee found agraine too light, as was this Phariſee. And therefore, <hi>ſine utroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que creſcere,</hi> let them both grow together untill the harveſt. Then the great husband-man ſhall come with his fanne in his hand, to purge his floore thorowly; the Wheate hee ſhall carry into his barne, but burne up the chaffe with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, let no ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary diſtraction, ſlacken thy hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py progreſſe to the Temple; but aſcend in body, and aſcend in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For this purpoſe, Temples were anciently ſcituated upon hils; as that at Ieruſalem upon mount <hi>Sion,</hi> a faire place, and the joy of the whole earth. Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers worſhipped in this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, (ſaid the woman of Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria) And many of our Temples are ſo ſcituated at this day. And moſt of them have certaine ſteppes or aſcents to Quires and Chancels,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13936:42"/> to teach thee to aſcend in ſpirit, aſwell as in body: to aſcend from the blindneſſe of nature to the light of grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from the old <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> of ſinne to the new man of righteouſneſſe; from affection to perfection; forſaking thy ſelfe and following thy Saviour.</p>
            <p>And when thou art come up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Temple, ſtand not up proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to juſtifie thy ſelfe, as did this Phariſee; neither ſquot downe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly in thy ſeat to ſleepe, as too many in this drowzy age; but fall low on thy knees with this Publican to pray. The Temple was not made to prate in, or to ſleepe in, but to pray in. Pray then, and be ſure to pray as thou oughteſt to pray. Pray humbly, pray heartily, pray devoutly, pray faithfully, and waver not. Feare not the two men that are about thee, or without thee, they can neither helpe nor hinder thy devotion; but let all thy care bee when thou commeſt into the Temple to pray, that there be not <hi>duo homines as and homine,</hi> two
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13936:42"/> men in one man within thee. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider where thou art, in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Conſider wherefore thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt thither, to pray. Conſider to whom thou ſpeakeſt by prayer, to to him that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a ſearcher of thy very heart and reines, and a diſcerner of thy ſecret thoughts long before thy ſelfe, and therefore will not be doubled or diſſembled with all. O conſider all this, thou that forgetteſt God and thy ſelfe too much, when thou goeſt up into the Temple to pray. Firſt, take <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonion</hi> for thy counſell: Be not raſh with thy mouth, nor let thine heart bee haſtie to utter a thing before God. Then take <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David</hi> for thy Preſidents. Put off the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſhoes of thy polluted affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, for the ground whereon thou treadeſt is holy ground. Firſt be able to ſay, <hi>Paratum eſt cor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Domine,</hi> My heart is ready, O God, my heart is ready: and then waſh thine hands in innocency and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe Gods altar.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:43"/>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:13936:43"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke 18. 11.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>The Phariſee ſtood and prayed with himſelfe thus,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE are paſt the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, and have made an entrance into the Parable it ſelfe ſo farre, as the behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the two men, whom it prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally concernes, the Phariſee and the Publican, is expreſſed joyntly in the Temple; where for a time we left them at thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> devotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and now have found them at it againe ſeverally, and apart,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13936:44"/> and firſt the Phariſee, for ſtill hee will be firſt.</p>
            <p>Who though he came into the Temple with the Publican, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, he prayes by himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. Whoſe devotion proclaimes him a preſumptuous hypocrite both in the manner, and in the matter. In the manner, by ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up ſo pert, and by ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. In the matter, which was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but meere braggery, bumba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his petitions, firſt with odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous commendations of himſelfe, privative, and poſitive; God I thanke thee I am no extortioner, no unjuſt man, no adulterer; but I faſt twice in the weeke, and I give tithe of all that I poſſeſſe. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by a malicious contempt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, generall and ſpeciall; I am not as other men are, nor as this Publican.</p>
            <p>The very manner of his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, plucks away the vale from his face, and fets him apparently up to the view of the whole world, that folly may bluſh, and wiſdome
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13936:44"/> be nothing aſhamed. And firſt it diſcovers the woodden head of ſelfe-confidence, which hath three parts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is his diviſion, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from the Church, taxed in this word, Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ifee; which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Hebrew <hi>Phares</hi> and <hi>Phareth,</hi> to divide 80 ſignifies the name of King <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whoſe regiment conſiſted of two forts of people, Hebrewes, and Egyptians. So <hi>Thamars</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>btwins, the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eth,</hi> but the elder called <hi>Pharez,</hi> beon uſe he firſt opened the wombe. So in that hand-writing againſt: <hi>Balthazar, MEN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> TEKEL PHARES or PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RES,</hi> Thon and thy kingdome are humbred, weighed, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to others.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond part of ſelfe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, is wilfull reſolution or o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of judgement, neither mooved by reaſon, nor removed by argument, intimat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the word, Standing.</p>
            <p>The third part of ſelfe-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13936:45"/> is either hereſie or any other imperfection of doctrine, implyed in theſe words, praying with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Three notable notes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt markes of a compleat Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the rending and ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of a mans ſelfe from the Congregation; if it be in matters of faith, it is called hereſie; if in matter of order or Ceremony, it is called Schiſme. Both which fall under the compaſſe of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> virge. They went out from us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not of us; for if they had beene of us, they would have continued with us: But this comes to paſſe, that it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare they are not all of us.</p>
            <p>Theſe two vipers and peſtilent brood of their mother Confuſion, have from the very beginning, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſnatched at the heeles, or flowne into the face of the true Church of God. The one, like thoſe men of Iabes Gilead will conclude no peace with Iſrael, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they may plucke out; their
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13936:45"/> right eyes. The other, like the young prince <hi>Ammon,</hi> ſhave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way halfe the beard, and cut off by the buttocks the garments of <hi>Davids</hi> Embaſſadours. So unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully is the Church crucified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two malefactors: The one doe <hi>diſrumpere charitatis vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Boys.</hi>
               </note> untie the bonds of peace; the other doe <hi>corrumpere fidei dogmata,</hi> undoe the unitie of the ſpirit. The firſt are different, in things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent; the ſecond almoſt indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, in matters different; and both ſpurne at the poore Church, as at a common football. Of all the world like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, ſevered in their head, but tyed together by the tayles, with fire-brands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, able to ſet a whole State in an uproare and a combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p>The Church is called in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a pillar, from whence they are fallen like a tottering roofe. A Ship, out of which they have wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully leaped to bee drowned, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſhipwracke of their faith. The
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13936:46"/> hill of Sion, from whence they have tumbled, and broken the necke of a good conſcience. And the Spouſe of Chriſt, whoſe love they have forſaken, like vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakers and adulterers.</p>
            <p>They can be content to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this to bee the true Church; and yet in a phariſaicall humour, they will not ſticke to cut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from it. Some for filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, teaching ſuch things as they ought not; as the Prieſt of <hi>Bell,</hi> and <hi>Hyminaeus,</hi> and <hi>Philetus,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> departing for the love of this preſent world. And as <hi>Paulus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſatenus,</hi> gaping for preſerment from <hi>Zenobia</hi> Queene of <hi>Arabia.</hi> Some for ambition, as <hi>Donatus,</hi> becauſe he could not get a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickei <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Carthage:</hi> And <hi>Novati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> miſſing the cuſhion for another in <hi>Italy:</hi> And <hi>Arrius</hi> greatly ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macking the matter, becauſe his ſchoole-fellow <hi>Euſtathius</hi> was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierome in</hi> 13. Zach:</note> conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Pontus,</hi> and not he. Some as ſicke as ever they can hold, of ſelfe-love; their very
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13936:46"/> conceit is their Idol. The covetous man worſhips his money; and the Hereticke his opinion; both like to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> worſhipping an unknowne God. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ſaid, hee was the great power of God the Father to the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> the Sonne to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Some amongſt us like the <hi>Manichees,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tertul.</note> who take their name from <hi>Manna;</hi> all that they ſay is Angels food. Some like <hi>Montanus,</hi> who ſaid he was the Comforter; none edifie but they. Some like <hi>Novatus,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe <hi>Moſes,</hi> and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Aaron</hi> their Paſtor and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Some like <hi>Donatus;</hi> there is no <note place="margin">Clem. Alex.</note> Church but in their <hi>Affrica,</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our charitie to wither like graſſe on the houſe top; and truth to bee diſguiſed like <hi>Ieroboams</hi> muffled wife, hardly to be known, and our concord to fall in pieces like ſand, and to be cut in the head like the greeke letter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>There was an harlot (you know) would not ſuffer <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:13936:47"/> to cut in pieces her living child; yet theſe miſcreants can indure to divide their ever-living Saviour. Some hold of <hi>Paul,</hi> ſome of <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> ſome of <hi>Cephas;</hi> who (if they had any grace) might at length heare their Saviour to complaine: I was torne with ſpeares, rent with nailes, ſhed my blood, and laide downe my life; <hi>ut te mihi conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerem,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. con. Ar.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; tu dividis me,</hi> to joyne thee to my ſelfe, and thou divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt mee.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is the head of the Church, and the Church is the fulneſſe of his body; as they are not to be divorced, ſo they ſhould not bee divided. The Olive Tree muſt be left with her fatneſſe; the <note place="margin">Iudg 9. 9.</note> Fig-tree with her ſweetneſſe; the Vine with her wine, that cheereth the heart of man; and the bramble buſh (forſooth) muſt bee annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted King, that men may truſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of her branches: As if wee could gather grapes of thornes, or figges of thiſtles. It is impoſſible to gather wholeſome
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13936:47"/> grapes (ſound doctrine, good life, true worſhip, dutifull ſubjection) of thornes (mutinous mindes, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent ſpirits, throats full of adders poyſon, feete ſwift to ſhed blood;) Or figges of thiſtles, (bread for hungry ſoules, certaine for doubting ſpirits, comfort for pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned conſciences:) they are both full of ſtinging prickes; malice and melancholly, humours and rumours, conceit and deceit, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order and diſcord, madneſſe and badneſſe, Thiſtles indeed, that have in their tops flowers like wooll, but are toſſed to and fro of every winde. Their libels are more then ſtanderous, their ſcoffes more then hiſtrionicall, and their calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions more then Sycophanticall, They would bee petty Popes in their pariſhes, Princes in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and <hi>Neroes</hi> after their five and few yeeres governement. <hi>Vtinam abſcindantur</hi> (ſay I with the Apoſtle) I wold to God they were even cut off that thus diſquiet you. They pretend that the zeale
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13936:48"/> of Gods houſe hath even eaton them up; when indeede the zeale of their owne houſes would eate up Gods houſe. Zealous <hi>Peter</hi> would faine build three taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; one for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> one for <hi>Moſes,</hi> and one for <hi>Elias:</hi> In that, hee wot not what hee ſaid; hee was wrapt. Zealous <hi>Boanerges, Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> thoſe Sonnes of thunder, at one time would faine have comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded lightning from heaven, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the unbeleeving <hi>Samaritans:</hi> at another time they deſired to ſit, the one at the right hand, the other at the left hand of Chriſt in his Kingdome. In neither of which, knew they of what ſpirit they were, or what they asked: Chriſt grants his Diſciples, no ſuch buſie warrants, as Antichriſt. <hi>Et ad quid perditio iſthaec</hi> (ſaid <hi>Iudas</hi> in his thriftie zeale) This oyntment might have beene ſold, and given to the poore: But wee all know he was a purſe-bearer.</p>
            <p>Zealous Iewes crucifie the Lord of light as a blaſphemer making
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13936:48"/> himſelfe the Sonne of God: And zealous Phariſes will part his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt them; even that <hi>tunicam inconſutilem,</hi> that ſeame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe coate, the Vnity of the faith, and pretend all conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſcience; they will looſe life and living, and yet not for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſake. Theſe are the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt bolts they ſhoote upon the ſuddaine, and the choiſeſt arrowes in all their quiver: All things they <note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> ſay are lawfull for them, but all things are not expedient. Which being ſpoken by the Apoſtle of things indifferent, nothing at all concerne matters of neceſſity. <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des docet quid debet, charitas quid decet:</hi> Our faith ſhewes us what is lawfull; our charity, what is expedient: And therefore the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Church are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, <hi>quoad benè eſſe,</hi> being the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterers of faith, and cheriſhers of charity.</p>
            <p>The ſecond arrow which is fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered with folly, ſhafted with errour, and armed with blindneſſe,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13936:49"/> is this, <hi>Stand faſt in the liberty which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> 
               <hi>yee have received in Chriſt Ieſus, and bee brought no more into the bondage of beggerly rudiments.</hi> Let them proove that they are the traditions of men, unwaſhed hands, the bondage of the world, and not the wholſome diſcipline of the true Church of God, inſpired by the holy-Ghoſt, warranted by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, admitted by Councels, and approoved by preſidents, and wee ſhall quickly yeeld. Otherwiſe it will bee told them, their colora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſinuations, and metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſhaddowes, <hi>à dicto ſecundum quid ad dictum ſimpliciter.</hi> The cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies Leviticall of the Law are aboliſhed, <hi>Ergo</hi> our Injunctions are abhominable? Such men ſuch matter. It is well knowne, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpeakes there of juſtification by workes and faith, and not of the ceremonies of the Goſpell. And yet (forſooth) theſe men in ſubſtance of religion can come and build with us, as did the men of Samaria by <hi>Zerubbabel;</hi> But to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13936:49"/> ſteale away the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as <hi>Abſolon</hi> did; Proclaiming faſts, as did <hi>Iezabel,</hi> but to maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre <hi>Naboth;</hi> Devouring Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes houſes in pretence of long prayer; they kiſſe like <hi>Iſcariot,</hi> but they kill like <hi>Iudas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If reaſonable and judicious men, would not willfully ſuffer themſelves to be hood-winked and flattered in their folly, they might eaſily diſcerne theſe Gibeonites, for all their rent ſackes, old ſhooes, dryed and moulded bread. I beare them record they have a zeale in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; I could rather wiſh they would have an inoffenſive conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence both towards God and Man; then would they bee ſure to give God his true feare, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due honour. And ſo I conclude this caſe of conſcience with Saint <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome: Si de veritate ſcandalum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Matt.</note> 
               <hi>utiliùs ſcandalum naſci per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, quàm veritas relinquatur.</hi> If ſome ſmall offence ſhould ariſe from the profeſſion of the truth,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13936:50"/> ſurely that offence muſt needs bee more tolerable, then groſſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. But when there is ſtrife, and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 3.</note> envy, and diviſion amongſt you, (ſaith the Apoſtle) are you not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? When one ſaith, I am <hi>Pauls;</hi> another, I am <hi>Apolloes;</hi> hearing one and hating another, are yee not carnall? I beſeech you brethren (in the Apoſtles heart and tongue) <hi>Marke them which cauſe contention amongſt you, and avoyde them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond part of Phariſaicall ſelfe-confidence, is a wilfull reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of opinion, or obfirmation of judgement intimated by the word, Standing. A flattering and confident arrogancy in it ſelfe, but uncharitably contemptuous unto others, begetting two grand-fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, an erroneous falſhood in the ſpeaker, and a doubtfull dubitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the hearer, and making both miſerable, when there are ſo many faiths, as there are wils in men; ſo many Doctors and doctrines, as manners in the world; and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſions of blaſphemies ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13936:50"/> as there are vices commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, till at length our faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion muſt be written as we liſt, and as wee liſt, it muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; when our Preachers like Spiders, weave Webs out of their owne bowels, and like deceitfull Vintners turne Wine into Water by falſifying texts, but never like Chriſt turne Water into Wine, by broaching ſound doctrines, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Word of God aright. When the hearers againe have itching eares, that cannot indure wholſome doctrines, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable conſtitutions; their will being, like unto a ſicke mans taſte, nothing is ſavoury; and their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment like the lightning that will bee ſeene before the thunder bee heard. <hi>Tertullian</hi> complaines much of their Preachers in his time: <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Scripturarum faciunt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ad ſuam materiam,</hi> They make a ſlaughter of the Scriptures for their owne purpoſe. And <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> as much of the hearers in his time. They run like mad
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13936:51"/> men into the wilderneſſe to ſee, and what doe they ſee? nothing but reeds ſhaken with the wind.</p>
            <p>Vaine-glory, is both the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the nurſe of obſtinacie. All that a Phariſee doth (ſaith our <note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> Saviour) is to be ſeene of men. He makes his Phylactery broad, and the fringes of his garment long. He loves <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the chiefe roomes at feaſts, the chiefe ſeats at Synagogues, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne greetings in the Markets, and to be called of men Rabbi, that his Science may be manifeſted, and himſelfe magnified; and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly, or indirectly. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly; if in words, it is called o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation; if in deeds, that have a face of truth, it is called invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but if the deeds be but appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent only, it deſerves no better a name then painted hypocriſie. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly; if in underſtanding, it is called pertinacy, and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of opinion; if in will, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention; if in plauſible ſpeech, and vociferation of words, contention;
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13936:51"/> if in action, it is called obſtinacy: So <hi>Iulian</hi> anſwering the chriſtian Epiſtles of the Biſhops: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <note place="margin">Sozom. l. 50. c. 18.</note> I read, I underſtood, and I deſpiſed. This is the phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaicall practice (I feare) of too many amongſt us, that being con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>victed by reaſon before prudent authori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, triumph at home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their populous ruſticity, as if they had gotten great ſpoyles; like S. <hi>Auguſtines, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natists, Disputare nolumus, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zare volumus;</hi> being more wordy then worthy, they ſpeake what they liſt, who ſhould controule them? <hi>Stat pro ratione voluntas;</hi> their will is their reaſon, and ſhall bee, though there bee no reaſon in their will, nor can bee: thou ſhalt not perſwade them though thou doeſt perſwade them: like <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> foole, the more they are brayed in the morter of diſcipline, the leſſe they ſeeme to underſtand; and, like the milke of a Tygre, the more they are ſalted, the freſher they are.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13936:52"/> A Phariſee ſits chiefe in Synods, ſpeakes firſt in Councels, runnes not ſent, intrudes not called, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords things ordered, undoes things done, cenſures them that have judged, prejudicates them that are to judge; and if hee bee not preferred when he would, and as hee would; either he preſently condemnes the ſuperiour as envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, himſelfe being malevolent, or elſe taxes his equall of Symony, himſelfe being full fraught with Sodomy.</p>
            <p>The Papiſt ſtands ſtiffely in his priviledge of provinciall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, uncanonicall verity, Church above Scripture, and Pope above both, making him in the plea, both party, and Iudge too. The Turke, in his <hi>Mahomets</hi> Alcaron, a golden booke of a leaden Saint. The <hi>Enthuſiaſtae,</hi> in their forced inſpiration, and ſuperilluminated brotherhood, being but new pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of the Shell, and ſcram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled into the Pulpit with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull contumely of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13936:52"/> and ſuch peremptory bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in themſelves, will ſpeake of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his numbers, <hi>Platoes Idea,</hi> the complots of a new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and a new earth, ripping up all ſecrets, as though they had beene wrapt up into the third hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, had the tongues of Angels, and the wiſedome of Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimes. On the other ſide the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers with unbridled tongues, and itching eares, kicke againſt the prickes, and beare them up in their hands, as <hi>Rachell</hi> did her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Idols. Some like <hi>Montanus</hi> his Diſciples tremble not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that their Teacher knowes as much or more then Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: Some like <hi>Carpocrates</hi> his Diſciples, that hee underſtands more then <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> with all haile unto their Seraphicall Rabbies; and <hi>Hoſanna, Hoſanna</hi> to their irrefragable Doctors, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying them, as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Schollers did their Tutor, with an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he ſaid it; and therefore it muſt be ſo. Or as dunce <hi>Carolus</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:13936:53"/> argued, it is ſo, becauſe it is ſo.</p>
            <p>Woe worth this multiplicitie of opinions, this wracking of Scriptures, and this ſqueezing and wire-drawing of texts, and this Phariſaicall pertinacy and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon it too, which is worſe then all the reſt. <hi>Humanum eſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, non retrahere belluinum, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verare diabolicum.</hi> It is the part of humane frailtie to fall into errour, of ſwiniſh beaſtlineſſe not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, but divelliſh pertinacy to perſiſt or to maintaine an errour. It is told in Gath, and it is reported in Askalon, that our kingdome is divided, and cannot long ſtand. It were to be wiſhed indeed, that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Andrew,</hi> would both Steere one courſe in this our Britiſh Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; that were the only way to keepe the net whole, and to catch moſt ſtore of fiſh. But howſoever I doubt not but I may ſafely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the malignant ſpirit, that hath moſt evill will at our Sion, as <hi>Simon Peter</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus; Vive, &amp; regnum Dci creſcere</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:13936:53"/> 
               <hi>videas, vel invitus:</hi> Long mayſt thou live, and to thy ſorrow ſee, the kingdome of God to increaſe mightily, even in this kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third and laſt part of pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaicall ſelfe-confidence is ſecreſie of doctrine, in that hee ſtands and prayes with himſelfe thus. Hee muſt have a vizard to cover his face bee it never ſo brazen, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt at one time or other it might bluſh. Hee flies like the Owle by night, and like a Lyon ſeekes his prey be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun-riſing. Every one that doth evill (ſaith our Saviour) <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> hates the light, neither comes hee to it, leſt his deedes ſhould bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved. But hee that doth truth, commeth to the light, that his deedes might bee made manifeſt, that they are wrought according to God. Phariſaicall hypocriſie is as naked as <hi>Adam</hi> after his fall, ſo miſerably aſhamed of himſelfe, that he runs into the buſhes at the voice of God. The truth is as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked too, but as <hi>Adam</hi> in the eſtate of innocencie; and therefore the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13936:54"/> bolder to appeare at the firſt call with <hi>Samuell,</hi> Speake Lord, for thy ſervant heareth: Or, to joyne in that grand challenge with <hi>Ieſus</hi> his authour and finiſher: <hi>Quis ex vobis arguet,</hi> Which of you can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke mee of ſinne? If I ſpeake the truth, why doe yee not beleeve mee? <hi>veritas non quaerit angulos,</hi> truth ſeekes no corners, I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken openly in the world, and in ſecret have I ſaid nothing.</p>
            <p>O Phariſee, phariſee, doeſt not thou know that our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands thee, <hi>Matthew</hi> 10. to <note place="margin">Mate. 10.</note> preach that upon the houſe top, which thou heareſt in the eare? Why doeſt thou then detract from the doctrine of the truth in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and carpe at the good life of thy brother in conventicles? with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all queſtion, <hi>Magna eſt veritas &amp; praevalet,</hi> Great is the truth and will prevaile: though ſome as Seminaries amongſt their Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers brag againſt us, and ſay, that we have a ſlight Apology for our faith. But as the King of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13936:54"/> to <hi>Benhadad,</hi> ſo may I ſay to theſe braggards: Let not him that <note place="margin">1 Kin 20.</note> girds on his harneſſe boaſt like him that puts it off; it muſt needes bee a ſilly triumph that is proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before victory. Some as <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionites,</hi> a generation that hath not ſet their heart aright, and whoſe ſpirit cleaveth not ſtedfaſtly unto God. Like as the children of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> which being harneſſed; and carrying bowes, turned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <note place="margin">Pſal. 7. 8.</note> backe in the day of battell: Crowing in their Pulpits a far off like cockes (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> makes the compariſon) and buſling their feathers like Turkies in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours: That would faine bind our Kings in chaines, and our Nobles in linckes of iron, and make Our Prieſts beleeve that God hath not ſpoken by them.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> wrot his Lawes in Cloſets and fathered them upon <hi>Veſta;</hi> ſo they paint op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious libels, and contentious bookes in corners with <hi>Venus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homets</hi> Alcaron was publiſhed in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13936:55"/> the night; and <hi>Prodicus</hi> his myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call communion, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men together, was celebrated when the candle was put out. When every man muſt have a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Ephod with <hi>Gedeon;</hi> or a whiſpering Levite with <hi>Micaiah;</hi> Religion muſt needes fall to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie with <hi>Ieroboam.</hi> In ſuch a caſe it is high time for <hi>Sampſon,</hi> a famous Iudge and Worthy of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael to tie his Foxes not onely by the tayles, but alſo by the heads together, in unitie and veritie of doctrine (as one of the Rabbins <note place="margin">Ben-ſira.</note> divinely adviſeth) that they may burne up the weedy corne of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> with the fire-brands of faith and truth, leſt they take both life and ſtrength from <hi>Sampſon</hi> himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Correct a wiſe man with a nod (ſaith <hi>Salomon)</hi> but a foole with a club. <hi>Cave nè circulus in ſylvam, gutta in mare, ſcintilla in ſlammam excreſeat:</hi> It is wholſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell from a Father; to beware that a ſmall waſte increaſe not to a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13936:55"/> vaſt wilderneſſe; a drop to a Sea; a ſparke to a flame. One jarring ſtring marres a whole conſort of muſicke; one rift hazzards a whole building; and a little leaven ſowres the whole lumpe: for if ſeveritie of diſcipline turne once into libertie, edification will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently run into deſtruction; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome into corruption; law into contempt; mercy into deriſion; godlineſſe into hypocriſie; preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into ſilence; the ſavour of life into the ſavour of death, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Thus farre (you ſee) wee have traced the Phariſee by his inward profeſſion in matter of Church doctrine, in a metaphoricall ſenſe; now the Text leads us to follow him a ſtep or two by his outward geſture in matter of Church diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline in a literall ſenſe: for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely they are both the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Holy Ghoſt, and ought to bee urged both; as moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and naturall to the analogy and proportion of faith.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:13936:56"/>
            <p>Where ſtill we ſhall bee ſure to find him a true Phariſee, a man di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; for hee divides himſelfe from his brethren, even in the Congregation too. He is too well acquainted with diſcord, and yet many times hee runs and out-runs himſelfe upon a point of diviſion. At a Feaſt hee will be ſure to take the upper roome, till hee bee bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with ſhame to ſit; lower. In the market hee mightily affect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſpective greetings. And in the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ple hee ſtands up by himſelfe like a Noune Subſtantive, amongſt the Eight parts of Speech; or an <hi>I per ſe</hi> I, amongſt the five vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells; as if his neighbours adjective devotion could not ſtand by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe without his Subſtantive; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were altogether inarticulate, as a ſentence wholly compoſed of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonants, without his vocall aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or aſſiſtant vocalitie: and why? becauſe hee thanke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s his God, he is not as other men are?</p>
            <p>This arrogant preſumption, and preſumptuous arrogancy, ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13936:56"/> upon his tip-toes; and makes him as ſtiffe in the joynts as an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, that hath no joynts at all. He ſtands, when he ſhould kneele, at prayer; he ſits, when he ſhould ſtand, at the Creed; and either he ſits or ſtands, when hee ſhould kneele, at the Sacrament. To be ſure to avoide <hi>artolatry,</hi> hee will not ſticke to commit <hi>autolatry;</hi> he is mightily afraid, where no feare is, to worſhip the bread; but hee feares not his owne proud inſolent carriage, whereby; in-ſtead of God, he worſhips himſelfe. In all the parts of Divine worſhip, both inward and outward, he is all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on contraries. The Church by her leave ſhall preſcribe him no forme, hee will have a will-worſhip by himſelfe; and why? becauſe hee thankes his God, he is not as other men are.</p>
            <p>Indeed he is not; nor as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould be, neither by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture precept, nor Scripture preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, which plead both for knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Divine worſhip. A Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13936:57"/> precept we gather, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19. 18. Where God expects from all trùe Iſraelites the bending of the knee only to himſelfe. Will the Phariſee beleeve God (thinke you) if he binde it with an oath? I referre him then to <hi>Eſay 25. 23. I have ſworne by my ſelfe</hi> (ſaith the Lord there) <hi>that unto mee every knee ſhall how.</hi> If the Phariſee dare attempt, in vaine, to make God forſworne; God ſhall ſweare once more, and hee ſhall not repent: This many fortie yeeres, have I beene grieved with the ſtubborne generation of this Phariſee, and therefore now will I ſweare in my wrath, that neither he, nor any of his, ſhall ever enter into my reſt.</p>
            <p>Should I muſter up the whole army Royall of Scripture preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents for this religious dutie of kneeling in Divine worſhip, I might be infinite. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to avoide prolixitie, draw out but ſome of the principall commanders, no leſſe then Kings
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13936:57"/> and Prophets, that have expreſſed the inward true humilitie of the heart, by the outward humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body; that the Phariſee may bluſh for ſhame, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhame in him, when wee ſhall object unto him the <hi>quot Reges &amp; Propheta,</hi> how many Kings, and Prophets, and deare Saints of God, and ſome after his owne heart too, have humbly deſired to imbrace this reverent geſture, which he out of an hautie ſpirit moſt proudly and ſcornefully refuſeth.</p>
            <p>Let him looke firſt upon <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> the wiſeſt, and wealthieſt, the moſt gracious and glorious prince (one only excepted) that ever the Iewes had, or the earth bare. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his gracefull geſture at the dedication of the Temple. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 6. 13. He made a brazen ſcaffold, hee ſet it in the middeſt of the Court, firſt hee ſtood upon it, then <note place="margin">2 Chron. 6. 13.</note> he kneeled downe upon his knees before all the Congregation of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and ſpread forth his hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven, and prayed. Let
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:13936:58"/> him look upon <hi>Daniel</hi> in the ninth <note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> of his Prophecie, and he ſhall finde him at his devotion, humbling himſelfe by faſting, and ſackeloth, and aſhes. Let him looke upon <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 16. And there he <note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> ſhall finde him lower then his knees, even flat upon his face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Maker. Let him looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King of Niniveh, <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 3. and behold the heathen Monarch, what ſtrange geſtures of heartie humiliation, he expreſſes in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtant act of his converſion. For no ſooner had hee heard that thundring Sermon from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, (yet fortie dayes and Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh ſhall be deſtroyed,) but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he aroſe, and ſtarts up, as if he had beene raiſed by an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake from his ſeat of honour and principalitie, his royall, his regall, magnificent, Monarchicall throne; He caſts his robe from him, with fury and indignation, as if his kingly attire of gold and purple had beene a burden to his backe, and as unſeemely to be worne as
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13936:58"/> the Egyptian ſcab. Hee covers himſelfe with ſackcloth, it is all the apparell now, that his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe deſires to weare; the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme to his head, the mantle to his backe, the ſandals to his feet; the King winds up his body in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, as a corps made ready for the buriall, humbling his duſt and earth to ſit in aſhes, that he might reade the Sonne of <hi>Sirachs</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of ſound humiliation effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to himſelfe: <hi>Quare ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis terra &amp; cinis?</hi> why art thou proud, oh earth and aſhes? hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſpirit, ſee thy mortalitie, tremble before the preſence of that God, that ſtrikes terrour into the hearts, and confuſion into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of all earthly Potentates.</p>
            <p>Let him looke upon the very King of Kings, and Prince of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Author and finiſher of our faith, even Ieſus the Mediator of the New Teſtament; who might juſtly ſay indeed, <hi>Non ſum ſicut cateri,</hi> I am not as other men are; neither proud, as thou Phariſee;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13936:59"/> nor ſinfull, as thou Publican: yet he, when hee was in the forme of God, and thought it no robbery, to be equall with God, humbled himſelfe to become man; and in the former part of his paſſive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience for the ſinne of man, fell downe upon his knees to prayer on the mount. As in the 22. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And to conclude all in a word; let him looke into the 26 of <hi>Iob.</hi> and <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. And hee ſhall finde that the very Pillars of heaven doe tremble, and are aſtoniſhed at the Majeſty of God; and the very Angels of Heaven doe fall upon their faces before the throne to worſhip God. Shall Kings, and Prophets, and the very Prince of Prophets; ſhall men and Angels, Saints and ſinners, Heaven and earth, and all the powers in both, quake and tremble, and fall low upon their knees, and flat upon their faces before the throne to worſhip their Maker; and onely the Phariſee ſtand up to juſtifie
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13936:59"/> himſelfe, and in the Temple too, and at prayer too and ſo devoutly by himſelfe too?</p>
            <p>There let him ſtand by himſelfe ſtill, as immoveable as his heart of ſtone that hee ſtands upon, or the pillar of ſtone that hee ſtands by. If either he thinkes hee may out-face his Maker, or challenge him upon a true debt, or taxe him upon his owne worthineſſe, or as a choice piece of clay diſpute with his potter, and convince him by dint of argument; hee may doe well to ſtand up by himſelfe ſtill, to boaſt, and bragge, and diſpute, and challenge: what need he pray? If otherwiſe, I muſt needes tell him, that one day there will come a miſerable humiliation for this proud exaltation: when hee that taxes him in this parable heere (and yet hee ſtands up proudly by himſelfe) ſhall come to taxe him the ſecond time with an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable company of Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in the cloudes, he ſhall never bee able to ſtand there. The man
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13936:60"/> that ſtood up ſo pertly upon his terms of righteouſneſſe here, ſhall never be able to ſtand up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt the righteous there. Then he ſhall fall downe, when it is too late, deſiring the hils to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, and the mountaines to fall upon him: then hee ſhall bee glad to humble himſelfe ſo low, as to annihilate himſelfe (if it were poſſible) to a meere nothing.</p>
            <p>And thus ends the firſt part of phariſaicall devotion, which is ſo corrupt (you ſee) in the very man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: The ſecond part, which is the matter, we ſhall find as corrupt in the next exerciſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:13936:60"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke 18. 11.</bibl>
               <q>God I thanke thee, that I am not as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men are, extortioners, unjuſt, adulterers, or even as this Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can.</q>
               <bibl>Verſ. 12.</bibl>
               <q>I faſt twice in the weeke, and I give tithe of all that I poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV have heard the corrupt manner of the Phariſees devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, now followes the matter as corrupt as it, being neither formall, nor effectuall, nor ſubſtantiall. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13936:61"/> it is not formall, it cannot be ſubſtantiall, by the principles of nature and grace too: For <hi>forma dat eſſe rei;</hi> without which devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe, is but a rude lumpe of indigeſted confuſion. And becauſe it is neither formall, nor ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, it cannot be effectuall, but as a founding braſſe, and as a tinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling cymball.</p>
            <p>Firſt, his devotion is corrupt in forme; He begins with an <hi>Ago gratias,</hi> God I thanke thee, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as mee thinkes a <hi>miſerere,</hi> would have became him better: Oh God, bee mercifull to mee a ſinner. A good Prieſt alwayes begins his devotion with a confeſſion of ſin, and ends with a thankſgiving or grace; as the Church Liturgie di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects him, and as all approoved ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in Scripture warrant him. <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18. petitioning for <note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> the Sodomites, proſtrated himſelfe before the Lord by an humble confeſſion of his owne weakneſſe: Behold, now I have begun to ſpeak unto my Lord that am but duſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13936:61"/> and aſhes. As if hee ſhould have ſaid; Oh let it not diſpleaſe my Lord; that I petition ſo earneſtly for ſinners, being a ſinner my ſelfe. So <hi>Iacoh Gen. 32. Minor ſum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> 
               <hi>miſerationibus tuis,</hi> O Lord I am not worthy the leaſt of all thy mercies. So <hi>David, 2 Sam.</hi> 7. <note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Quis ego, &amp; quae domus mea?</hi> who am I, O Lord, &amp; what is my houſe, that thou haſt brought mee hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? So <hi>Daniel</hi> 9. We have ſinned, <note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> and have committed iniquitie, and have done wickedly; O Lord, righteouſneſſe belongeth unto thee, but unto us open ſhame. But this Map of irregularitie begins at the wrong end with an <hi>Ago gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias,</hi> and in ſtead of accuſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe condemnes his brother: In generall, <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri,</hi> I am not as other men are; In ſpeciall, <hi>non ſicut iſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Publicanus,</hi> I am not as this Publican; <hi>for I faſt twice in the weeke, and I give tithe of all that I poſſeſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this makes his devotion as corrupt in ſubſtance as in forme,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13936:62"/> puft up with nothing but battolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and tautologies, and idle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions. Hee might aſwell have expreſſed all his perfections by that one word <hi>juſt,</hi> as did the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican his imperfections by that one word <hi>ſinner:</hi> for if he were juſt hee could bee no extortioner; and if no extortioner, without queſtion hee payed his tithes; and if he faſted often, it argues that he was continent; and if more righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous then all men, it muſt needs bee granted, that he was more juſt then the Publican. But it ſeemes this vaine babler loves to heare himſelfe talke; as if he came not to pray unto his God, but to prate unto his owne ſweet-ſelfe. As <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> upon the place, and as the words of the text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely inſinuate: <hi>The Phariſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtood, and prayed with himſelfe thus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His devotion then, beeing ſo voide of forme, and voide of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, cannot chooſe but be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ineffectuall: for marke
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13936:62"/> firſt how arrogantly he pleades, <hi>Non ſum ſicut cateri;</hi> I am not as other men are. It had beene an extreme point of arrogancie, to have advanced himſelfe above ſome men, or above moſt men; but to vilifie and contemne all men, and eſpecially the penitent Publican, it muſt needes bee the part of an incarnate Lucifer, and more then the ſpice of <hi>Ero ſimilis altiſſimo;</hi> I will bee like unto the moſt high, and place my neaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove amongſt the ſtarres of God. For upon earth (you ſee) hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges no man equal to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Whereby he ſeemes migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to diſparage both the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the goodneſſe of God; as if God were bound only to bleſſe, and to inrich him.</p>
            <p>And therefore the ſinne of pride is moſt aptly compared to a whirlewind, that turnes up whole Cedars by the rootes; and to its power will indure nothing to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt before it. There is no ſinne elſe but will bee ſociable, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13936:63"/> of too many companions: on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this divelliſh pride is of ſo ſterne, and auſtere a nature, that it brookes no equall: it exalts itſelfe not only againſt all that is called man, but all that is called God.</p>
            <p>Againe, marke how ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly hee pleades: <hi>I faſt twice in the weeke, and I give tithe of all that I poſſeſſe.</hi> As if a begger ſhould come to the doore and aske an almes, and ſhew his Rings and Robes, and coſtly ornaments; a man would thinke that rags and wounds would ſooner ſpeed his ſuite: So this proud begger, or bragger rather, ſhews not his rags, but his robes; not his wounds, but his worth; not his miſerie, but his braverie: <hi>Ergojam plenus es Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> (ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon the place) Hee is full, and needes not almes; he is whole, and needs <note place="margin">Reu. 3. 17</note> no phyſitian: He thankes his God, with the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> That he is rich in grace, and increaſed in goods, and wants nothing; and Knowes not that hee is wretched,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13936:63"/> and miſerable, and poore, and blinde, and naked.</p>
            <p>The caſe of ſuch a man muſt needs be as deſperate as that ſicke patients, that having a veine ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a Chirurgeon, lets out his beſt blood that maintaines life, and onely retaines the worſt that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens death: So this Phariſee here, lets out all his goodneſſe at once, that ſhould maintaine his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all health; and keepes his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cloſe to himſelfe; the onely ſpeedy way to haſten his everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting death. Yet ſuch are the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, that theſe fooles offer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to the Almightie. It is the language of <hi>Balaam, Num.</hi> 23. <note place="margin">Numb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5</note> when his Maker met him; <hi>ſeptem altaria ordinavi,</hi> I have prepared ſeven altars, and offered upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very altar a Bullocke and a Ram: As if God were ſo reſpectleſſe that he would not, or ſo blind that hee could not ſee the beſt of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Wee neede not feare the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſciencie of God, who ſees not only the deede but the will, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13936:64"/> duely weighs and conſiders every circumſtance of both. Let <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> teſtifie, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 22. Hee was ready there to offer up the ſacrifice enjoyned him by the Angel, with an <hi>Ecce ego</hi> twice, Behold heere I am. At the firſt call to receive the <hi>fiat,</hi> Heere: At the ſecond call to act the <hi>fiat,</hi> Heere. And God was as ready to conſider, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and to reward every cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of his obedience, ſo wracked and tortured upon ſuch a multiplicitie of difficulties, with a <hi>quia feciſti hanc rem.</hi> By my ſelfe I have ſworne (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt done this thing, and haſt not ſpared thine onely ſonne: Therefore I will ſurely bleſſe thee, and greatly multiply thy ſeede.</hi> As if God ſhould have ſaid unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> thus. <hi>Abraham,</hi> I ſee thy will, and I ſee thy deed, and I accept thy will for thy deed; and I weigh and conſider every circumſtance of both to bee full of difficultie. I ſee thou art ready for my ſake to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, not a beaſt, but a man; not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13936:64"/> a ſervant, but a ſonne; not one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many, but an only Sonne; and he not an ordinary, or a diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected Sonne, but a beloved <hi>Iſaac,</hi> upon whoſe life depends the whole burden of the promiſed bleſſing. All theſe circumſtances I weigh, as weighty and ponderous indeede; and by my ſelfe I ſweare, <hi>quia feciſti hanc rem,</hi> Becauſe thou haſt done this thing, this great thing, this thing beyond a name; Therefore I will ſurely bleſſe thee, and greatly multiply thy ſeed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Magdalen, Luk.</hi> 7. can teſtifie the like; who received ſuch ſtrange approbation from our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, for that poore entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhe gave him, for anointing his feete; that hee weighed and conſidered every circumſtance, to the great diſparagement of <hi>Simon</hi> the houſe-keeper. For, turning to the woman, and ſpeaking unto <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> he ſaid: <hi>Seeſt thou this woman? I entred into thine houſe, and thou gaveſt me no water to my feete; but ſhe hath waſhed my feete with teares,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13936:65"/> and wiped them with the haires of her head. Thou gaveſt me no kiſſe; but ſhe, ſince the time that I came in, hath not ceaſed to kiſſe my f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ete. Mine head with oyle didſt thou not annoint; but ſhe hath annointed my f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ete with ointment.</hi> Marke how hee obſerves every circumſtance of his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement, and accordingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it with a boone, no leſſe then a <hi>peccata remittuntur:</hi> Thy ſinnes are forgiven thee.</p>
            <p>It is bootleſſe then for any man to play the Phariſee ſo deepely, as to divulge his goodneſſe, and to conceale his wickedneſſe, and to, and from Him too, that is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall and an impartiall diſcerner of both. To proclaime that to him, that knowes it long before our ſelves, it is extreame tolly; to hide that from him, to whom all things are open, it is extreame frenzie. Hee cannot poſſibly bee the better by the one, but hee muſt needs be a great deale the worſe by the other; and indeede to ſay the truth, a great loſer by both.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:13936:65"/>
            <p>That the Phariſee went up into the Temple to pray; that hee was not an extortioner, unjuſt, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; that hee faſted, and payed his tithes, were things (no doubt) both exceeding commendable, and abſolutely commandable: for theſe things hee ought to have done. But his proud boaſting, like the herbe <hi>Coloquintida,</hi> or wilde gourd mentioned, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">2 King 4.</note> the whole pot of pottage. <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le virtutibus affluens propter arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantiam falicitatem amiſit:</hi> The wonderfull vertuous man, is now become wonderfull vicious; He, that before was happly none, is now unhappily become an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioner in the higheſt degree, robbing God of his due honour, and relying wholly upon his owne merits. Hee that before might bee comparatively juſt, is now moſt unjuſt beyond compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, taking the wall of his betters, and condemning the Publican raſhly without proofe or reaſon, or any due forme of Law; playing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13936:66"/> the part of an accuſer and a Iudge too. Hee, that before might bee little or none, is now become an adulterer in the higheſt degree, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo wedded unto the world, and wholly enamoured with popular applauſe, not knowing (like an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer as hee is,) that the amitie of the world, is but enmitie with God. So that in fine (you ſee) like a fooliſh Hen he loſt all his eggs by cackling; hee did <hi>verbis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre virtutem</hi> indeed, but hee did <hi>factis deſtruere veritatem</hi> too. Like <note place="margin">Cypr.</note> an emptie mill, the more the clacke goes, the leſſe the mill grindes.</p>
            <p>Such is the dangerous nature and condition of ſecret pride; It can make nothing more, but it doth make all things leſſe; and yet even then ſeeming greateſt in ſhew, when they are leſt in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: Like the painting of an harlot, it cozens all, and yet it drawes moſt men after it. It is the divels owne darling, and therefore muſt needs bee moſt acurate to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:13936:66"/> All other ſinnes are but his baſtards, this is his owne brat, and like the father; his expreſſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, as <hi>Bernard</hi> cals it. All other ſinnes (as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) <note place="margin">Bern. Aquin.</note> are ſaid to bee in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell <hi>ſecundum reatum,</hi> by guilt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as being the tempter to every ſinne: only pride and envie is in him <hi>ſecundum effectum;</hi> as being the firſt actor of this ſinne in his owne perſon.</p>
            <p>This makes the politicke Jeſuite abroad, and the crafty Iebuſite at home ſuch mighty mount-bankes of their owne perfections, and roaring trumpets of their owne vaine-glory; thanking their God, that they are not as other men are, nor as wee, caſt-awayes; but <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectioris farinae</hi> men of a purer note, and cleerer converſation; thinking nothing but truth, ſaying nothing but truth, doeing nothing but truth. Eſpecially the Ieſuite will not be perſwaded, but that the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimple of all mens actions, words, and thoughts, are in his free gift,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13936:67"/> to raiſe, and ſet the price at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. His <hi>entia</hi> be <hi>tranſcendentia;</hi> in all things an abſolute Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative, <hi>ſans peere.</hi> His very ſots are <hi>Salomons,</hi> his blacke-birds Swans, and his ſilents politickes. Hee is the very ſpawne and frie of the old Phariſee; of whom I may too juſtly ſay, as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the Manichee: <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Si hoc eſſet juſtum eſſe, juſtificare ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum;</hi> if this were to be juſt for a man to juſtifie himſelfe, certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this generation of Vipers had long ſince flowen up into heaven in the whirlewind of their owne imaginations: but examine their actions, and you ſhall find <hi>Davids</hi> clogge at their heeles, that weighs them downe. They travell with miſchiefe, they conceive ſorrow, and they bring forth ungodlineſſe. Their throat is an open ſepulchre, <note place="margin">Pſal. 5. 9.</note> they flatter with their tongue, there is no faithfulneſſe in their mouth, their inward parts are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>And indeed to ſay the truth, this
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13936:67"/> makes every man, almoſt without exception, ſo familiar with this <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri,</hi> (I am not as other men are, or as that Publican) that I feare I might too juſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert our Saviours queſtion to the Iewes, and ſay, <hi>Quis ex vobis non argueretur de peccato hoc?</hi> which of you may not in ſome ſort bee taxed of this ſinne? <hi>Quis non Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaeus?</hi> who hath not in one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or other, ſome dreg, ſome ſpice of a Phariſee; ſome more, ſome leſſe?</p>
            <p>The glutton, and the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, hee thankes his God too, that hee is not as other men are: Extortioner, unjuſt (adulterer perhaps) but not as that uſurer, Hee faſts little, hee confeſſes; but hee payes his tithes as freely as he drinkes, and that is commonly more then his ſhare for quietneſſe ſake. And indeed well may hee thanke the god hee ſerves for it, his belly; which makes him draw ſo large a patrimony thorow his throa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, that eaſes him of all care,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13936:68"/> either for uſe or principall.</p>
            <p>The Vſurer, and Extortioner, he thankes his god too, that he is not as other men are. A little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt perhaps? but ſure hee is no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer, no glutton, nor as that drunkard; he faſts enough in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, all the weeke long, both he and his family to ſave charges: and hee payes tithe for as much of his poſſeſſion as the Law can ſqeeze out of him. But hee too may thanke the god hee ſerves for all this, his gold; to whom hee is ſo proſtrate by a certaine kinde of ſuperſtition, that upon paine of ſacriledge, he dares ſcarce lay fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note place="margin">Auri Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra fames Virg</note> on it, even for pinching ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, much leſſe for ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>The riotous, and voluptuous ſwaggerer, hee thankes his god too, that hee is not as other men are; wracking extortioners, gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Vſurers, unjuſt oppreſſors, or as that plodding worldling. Hee ſcornes to bee ſo baſe to lade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with thicke clay; or that the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:13936:68"/> ſtone ſhould cry out of the wall to him, or the beame out of the tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber anſwer it. For adultery, tuſh, it is but a tricke of youth: faſting <note place="margin">Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unium coactum.</note> hee is content to imbrace when he can get no victuals: Hee neither ſowes, nor reapes; and therefore neither cares for tithes, nor any thing elſe: for his part hee will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſure to make much of one ſo long as it holds; Eate, drinke, and bee merry, and let the world wagge. But alas little doth this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad-man dreame, how ſoone this god hee thankes, and this maſter he ſerves, his body of ſinne, will turne him out of doores with ſlender wages, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> at moſt, the periſhing pleaſures of ſinne for a ſhort reaſon; like <hi>Iona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his gourd, ſoone Worme-eaten, and ſoone withered.</p>
            <p>But why ſpend wee time about theſe vicious men? This leaven of the Phariſee, a ſecret conceipt of the <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri,</hi> hath both ſowred and ſwelled the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt profeſſors in the ſchoole of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:13936:69"/> vertue and godlineſſe too. In ſo much that it is obſerved by ſome, that this devilliſh pride hath not onely raiſed all vices, either pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely or privately, but all vertues againſt humility too. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Concute, tecum habita, te con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſule, dic tibi quis ſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let every man plumbe deepe into his owne conſcience, and tell me, whether hee bee not ſecretly proud of his giving of almes, proud of his faſting, proud of his praying; and, if he pay his tithes duly, whether he be not ſecretly proud of that too? It is likewiſe obſerved further, that this infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall haggard hath ſet humility at variance with her ſelfe, lift up her hand to offer violence to her owne perſon, and by a monſtrous, unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, prodigious kinde of birth to bring forth pride: In ſo much that the humble man is too often as proud of his humilitie as <hi>Diogenes</hi> of his ragges. It is high time then for that great Actor and Teacher of humility it ſelfe, to deliver unto
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:13936:69"/> us that wholeſome caveat in the Goſpell: <hi>Beware of the leaven of the Phariſes;</hi> for it ſoures all, and it ſwels all: when the heart is once ſecretly infected with it, it ſends up ſuch a bitterneſſe out of the ſtomacke in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the mouth, that men ſorbeare not to ſpeake evill of ſuch as are in authority; much leſſe to vilifie their equals or inferiors, with a <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri,</hi> I am not as other men are, or as that Publican.</p>
            <p>Oh that men would once purge out this old leaven, that they might bee a new lumpe, and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate a perpetuate feaſt of ſweet bread unto the Lord their God with the unleavened bread of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and truth: which with hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty prayer, and honeſt Chriſtian en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour they might in time accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh, if they would but obſerve and practiſe this our rule. When a man lookes upon his neighbour, let him obſerve his vertues, and not his vices; when he lookes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf, let him take notice of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13936:70"/> his owne vices, but not his vertues. An excellent pill to purge out the old leaven, if it be truly obſerved and duly kept; the breach of either clauſe whereof opens a large gap unto the <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri,</hi> I am not as other men are, or as that Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican.</p>
            <p>For example ſake: when a man undertakes the burden of his owne actions, hee put his vices into the hinder part of the Wallet, and caſts them behind his backe; but his vertues he will be ſure to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry before him in the former part of the Wallet. His vices are no ſooner acted but forgotten; but his vertues are many times pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed before they are acted. Let him bee taxed for vice, and preſently hee pleades. Either <note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> King in Ion.</note> 
               <hi>non feci;</hi> Or, <hi>ſi feci, non male feci;</hi> Or <hi>ſi male, non multum male;</hi> Or <hi>ſi multum male, non mala intentione;</hi> Or <hi>ſi mala intentione, aliena tamen perſwaſione:</hi> Either he did it not; Or if that be prooved, then he did not ill in ſo doing; Or if that bee
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13936:70"/> made manifeſt, then it was not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill done: a ſmall fault God knowes. Is it not a little one and my ſoule ſhall live? Or if it bee prooved to bee a great one, <hi>horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum facinus,</hi> then God forgive him for it, it was done againſt his will, hee had no intention in the world to doe it: or if his ill intent be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, then, true it is indeed, it was a great weakneſſe of his to be ſo fooliſhly lead and drawne to it by the perſwaſion and inſtigation of others, Thus are moſt men too familiar in begetting, but too ſtrange in fathering their baſtard vices; they will bee ſure to have one tricke or an other to ſlip them (if it may be poſſible) into the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of the Wallet, and carry them unto their graves, as if they had never beene. But let him bee commended for vertue, and hee preſently anſwers like a pert <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan—Coràm quem quaeritis adſum:</hi> and if no man take notice of his goodneſſe, hee commonly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimes it himſelfe, he carries it in
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13936:71"/> the former part of the Wallet, and for a need he can be the trumpeter of his owne praiſes.</p>
            <p>But when a man beares the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of another mans actions, hee puts his vices into the former part of the wallet, and his vertues into the hinder part, to verifie that old proverbiall <hi>diſtichon:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe a man ill, he heares of that ever:</p>
            <p>Doe a man well, he heares of that never.</p>
            <p>As it was affirmed of <hi>Peter,</hi> after he denied his Maſter; <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cata vides, lachrymas non vides,</hi> And as the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers of the Adultreſſe behaved themſelves. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. Good God, how <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> skilfull, and buſie they were in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting the poore womans folly. Firſt, they tooke her (ſaith the text.) Secondly, In the act. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they ſet her in the middeſt. Fourthly, they urge the Law of. <hi>Moſes,</hi> and needs they muſt have her ſtoned to death forſooth. <hi>Peccata vident,</hi> they ſee her ſinne, it is plaine and evident, and they aggravate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13936:71"/> circumſtance to the full: <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymas non vident,</hi> her teares of true repentance they ſee not, they caſt them into the hinder part of the wallet: And therefore our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, that knew all ſecrets both hers and theirs, gives the wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let but the right turne, bids him, that was without ſinne, caſt the firſt ſtone; And preſently (ſaith the text) they went out one by one, and Ieſus and the woman were left alone. So the womans accuſers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their owne accuſers: they found that writing, which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour drew in the duſt, ſo deepely ingraven in their owne hearts with a pen of iron, it could not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee, if that every man would but doe as he ought, beare one anothers burden in love, and give the wallet but the right turne; this leaven of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, which is no better then ſecret pride, and divelliſh hypocriſie, would quickly bee converted into the unleavened bread of truth and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:13936:72"/> ſinceritie. If every man, when he carries his owne burden, would but turne his vice before him, and his vertue behind him; it would both mightily further his humiliation, and ſlacken his oſtentation. If when he carries an other mans burden, he would but turne the vertue before him, and the vice behind him; it would mightily further his owne edification, and ſlacken the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and vilification of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then would hee judge no man raſhly before the time, but paſſe the verdit of guiltineſſe only upon himſelfe here, that hee may eſcape the ſevere cenſure of the Lord hereafter. Then would the ugly ſhape of his owne vice mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie him, and the exemplary ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his neighbour quicken him. And then would hee turne the ſtreame of the <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri,</hi> quite an other way; And when he comes up into the Temple to pray, after an humble confeſſion of ſinne upon his bended knees, hee would powre out an heartie thankſgiving
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:13936:72"/> for his firſt fruits of grace, after this, or the like manner.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, (a fit prayer for thoſe <note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Featly</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide to private Devotio.</note> to make, that have falne ſince their Baptiſme into groſſe ſinnes,) O Lord, the time was not long ſince, that I walked in darkeneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death; in the errour of mine underſtanding, the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my will, the diſorder of mine affections, the impuritie of my thoughts, the vanitie of my deſires, the dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itfulneſſe of mine heart, and the wickedneſſe of of all my wayes. The God of this world had ſo blinded mine eyes that I thought my ſelfe moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, when indeed I was moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; and the leaven of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee had ſo ſowred and ſwelled mine heart, that I only advanced my ſelfe, and vilified my brother. But now, God I thanke thee, thou haſt given mee the grace to begin to ſee my wretchedneſſe. <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri;</hi> indeed, it is true, I am not as other men are, nor as this Publican. They are juſt, I unjuſt:
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13936:73"/> they none extortioners, nor adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers; I both in the higheſt degree, I have robbed thee of thine honour, wedded my ſelfe wholly to the world, and beene puft up with the vaine blaſt of popularitie: They have beene temperate in the comfortable uſe of thy good crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I have beene often ſuffocated and crop-ſicke with the ſwiniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of them; and with my fellow glutton in the Goſpel, have fared deliciouſly every day: They have payed their tithes juſtly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, without grutching or grumbling, not for feare of the Law, but for the maintenance of the Goſpel; I have pinched and purloined ſometimes halfe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times all thy portion for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of mine owne divelliſh pride and ſenſualitie. <hi>Vae miſero,</hi> oh miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliver mee from the body of this death? God I thanke <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> thee through Ieſus Chriſt my Lord, that thou haſt given mee this ſingular grace, at length to ſee this
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:13936:73"/> great wretchedneſſe of mine: The conſideration whereof muſt needs humble mee in my ſelfe, that Chriſt may raiſe me; wound me in my ſelfe, that Chriſt may heale me; burden me in my ſelfe, that Chriſt may eaſe me; kill mee in mine owne conceipt, that Chriſt may quicken me; and make mee moſt vile and deſpectible in mine owne eyes, that I may bee moſt precious in his ſight: For now, God I thanke thee, I ſee moſt cleerely, <hi>Non ſum ſicut caeteri.</hi> I am not as other men are, nor as this Publican.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:74"/>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:13936:74"/>
            <head>THE FIFTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke 18. 13.</bibl>
               <q>But the Publican ſtanding a farre off, would not lift up ſo much as his eies to heaven, but ſmote his breſt, ſaying, O God bee mercifull to mee a ſinner.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE have ſufficiently ſcanned every part and particle of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaicall devotion, occaſioned by the precedent paſſages of this parable; which we found to bee altogether corrupt, both in the manner, and in the matter. But now this Text
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:13936:75"/> preſents unto us a matchleſſe mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of pure devotion with a (But) indeede; which puts a Diametri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call oppoſition betwixt the two Supplyants, and their ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions. The Phariſee and the Publican ſtand (both) at firſt; The Phariſee in the moſt eminent and perſpicuous place of the Temple, as if he had beene the only profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of pietie; But the Publican a farre off in ſome obſcure or darke corner, as a meere caſt-away in his owne conceit. The Phariſee prayes by himſelfe in the middeſt of the Congregation, as judging him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the beſt of the Congregation: But the Publican by himſelfe in the very skirts of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as judging himſelfe not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the communion of Saints. The Phariſee ſtood up to juſtifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to diſpute with his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker; to advance himſelfe, and to vilifie his brother: But the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican would not lift up ſo much as his eyes to heaven, but vilifie and debaſe himſelfe below the greateſt
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:13936:75"/> Sinner: The Phariſees devotion was ſowre and tedious; contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as many lines as the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, words; But the Publicans was ſhort and ſweete, every word a ſentence, coutching much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a little roome, <hi>Oravit paucis,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bucer.</note> 
               <hi>ſed affectu multo,</hi> (as <hi>Bucer</hi> upon the place) Expreſſing by three poſtures, and foure words, the foure capitall vertues of a true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent; Contrition, Confeſſion, Faith, and Amendment. His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition was aboundantly manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the humble diſtance of place he kept, Standing a farre off; by his dejected countenance, not preſuming ſo much as to lift up his eyes to heaven; and by ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his hand upon his breſt. His confeſſion, by acknowledging himſelfe to bee a ſinner. His faith by calling upon God in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of his feare, and knocking his breſt to rouſe up his heart; and by applying the mercies of God in Chriſt unto himſelfe by a timely <hi>Miſerere. O God, be mercifull to me a</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:13936:76"/> 
               <hi>ſinner.</hi> And for the amendment of his life, that likewiſe followed in its order: For hee went home (ſaith our Saviour) unto his houſe j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtified: nor are wee to doubt but that hee, after this, brought forth fruite worthy of amendment of life.</p>
            <p>Behold then in this humble Publican an incomparable pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of pure devotion, right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the note and imitation, both for the matter, and for the manner. For the manner (mee thinkes) hee performes the office of a skilfull Organiſt, who commonly keepes the remoteſt place of diſtance from the Altar, ſtanding a farre off: And though his fantaſie bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly wrapped with a concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an heavenly aire, yet his countenance is outwardly deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and caſt downe, not ſo much as lifting up his eyes to heaven: But for his hand, it is agill and nimble for want of an aſſiſtant to blow the bellowes, by ſmiting the breaſt; the bellowes being full to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:13936:76"/> ſend it into the trunke of the heart; the keyes of the heart being touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to let it into the pipes, and ſo to begin his ſervice.</p>
            <p>For the matter (me thinkes) he makes up a compleate Quire, of himſelfe, and ſings a ſolemne Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of foure parts. <hi>A Iove princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium:</hi> He beginnes upon a treble, and an high one too, no lower then the higheſt; happy is hee that can reach him, ſure I am there isnone can over-reach him, <hi>O God.</hi> The Diapaſon to that is a Baſe, and a deepe one too, <hi>De profundis cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat.</hi> Out of the deepes hee cryes with that ſweete Singer of Iſrael, becauſe a Sinner. And the two clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing parts, that give the reliſh, and make the muſicke full, are a true Tenor, that alwaies ſings <hi>me in Ela me,</hi> upon a ſharpe ſtraine of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; and a ſweete Meane, that clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes up all upon a flat ſtraine of mercy: And the ſame heart and hand, that give breath unto the pipes, beate time unto the Song, <hi>O God, be mercifull to mee a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:13936:77"/>
            <p>I ſuppoſe I neede not call for your eares to hearken to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, being ſo muſically divine, and divinely muſicall, and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and pertinent to the Text and time. Wherein firſt the manner of his devotion directs us to his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble poſtures, and firſt to his <hi>Stat à longè: The Publican ſtanding a farre off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtrength of his devotion brought him into the Temple to pray; but when he came thither, the guilt of his owne ſinne, the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of his owne conſcience, the fearefulneſſe of the place, it ſelfe being the houſe of God, the habitation of the moſt High, the place where his honour dwelleth; All theſe meeting together in his perplexed thoughts, with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>peccata diviſerunt,</hi> Your ſins have made a ſeparation betwixt your God and you; laid ſuch a blocke at the feete of his forward zeale; that, ſtanding a farre off, he durſt not approach neerer, till hee had obtained a plenarie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:13936:77"/> abſolution, by the meanes of an humble and hearty confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Propitius eſto Deus mihi pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catori. O God, be mercifull to mee a Sinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to aſſure you that this is the right poſture of true humilitie in divine Service, for a ſinner to acknowledge and bewaile his long diſtance from God, before he can drawe neere unto him; wee have a Prodigall in another Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in this Goſpel to paralel the Publican. Who when he had ſpent <note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> all his goods by ryotous living in a farre Countrey, in ſo much that he would faine, if hee had beene ſuffered, have eaten huskes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Swine for hunger, no ſooner came to himſelfe, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he found and bewailed his farre diſtance from his Fathers houſe, where the very hired ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants had bread enough, and hee ready to die for hunger. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he preſently reſolves to ariſe, and to goe to his Father, and ſay; Father, I have ſinned againſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:13936:78"/> and againſt thee, and am no more worthy to bee called thy Sonne; make mee but as one of thine hired Servants. But before he found himſelfe to be a ſtranger, there was no thought of home.</p>
            <p>Surely (beloved) it was not onely that Prodigals, or this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, but it is every ſinners caſe; if men would but rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand themſelves. Too many there are (I feare) that thinke they are ſtayed children at home in their Fathers houſe, when indeede, they are no better then unthriftie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digals, waſting and conſuming their portions in a farre Countrey. Too many that are too audacious to preſſe into the Houſe of God, without either feare or wit to keepe their true diſtance: For le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> every man be aſſured and reſolved of this; whoſoever ſhall preſume to draw neere unto God with his lips onely, and cloſe in with him upon a ſodaine, by an arrogant advancement of his owne worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, God ſhall ſtand off as farre
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:13936:78"/> from him as from this Phariſee: But whoſoever ſhall ſtand trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling a farre off, by an hearty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſinne, and an humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of his owne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe, God ſhall drawe as neere unto that man, as unto this Publican.</p>
            <p>The ſecond poſture of true hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, expreſſed by this humble Publican, was the dejection of his countenance: <hi>Nolebat oculos ad coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum levare,</hi> Hee would not ſo much as lift up his eies to heaven, or to his Father, which was in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: He knew and acknowledged with the aforeſaid Prodigall, that he had ſinned againſt heaven, and againſt his heavenly Father, and that he was no more worthy to be called his Sonne. This was <hi>Eſdras</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſd. 8. Luk. 7.</note> his poſture, Who confeſſed unto the Lord, That hee was aſhamed, and confounded before His face. It was likewiſe <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> in the ſeaventh of this Goſpel; Who thought her ſelfe unworthy by reaſon of her manifold tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:13936:79"/> to appeare before the face of her bleſſed Saviour; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when He ſate at Table in the Phariſes houſe, ſhee ſtood trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling behind him, brought a boxe of oyntment, proſtrated her ſelfe at His feete, waſhed them with her teares, and wiped them with the haires of her head, and kiſſed them, and anoynted them with oyntment, and never preſumed to ſhew her face either to him or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, before ſhe had received thoſe bleſſed words of abſolution, <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata remittuntur,</hi> thy ſinnes are forgiven thee.</p>
            <p>Certainly (beloved) ſuch is the ugly ſhape and diſguiſe of ſinne; that if but every ones Rimmon were written in his fore-head, wee ſhould not meet one another in the ſtreets with that boldneſſe that we doe, much leſſe croude into the Temple to juſtifie our ſelves with ſuch impudence, and erection of countenance. Many a man (ſaith <hi>Tacitus)</hi> carries a ſmooth face out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, <note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> 
               <hi>Quonum ſi mentes reclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantur,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:13936:79"/> poſſint adſpici laniatus &amp; ictus;</hi> if a man could but turne their inſide outward, hee might ſoone diſcover ſtrange ſtripes, and rents, and galles of conſcience. The reaſon is, becauſe the griefe is inward, gnawing and feeding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an heart as hard as brawne, and therefore inſenſible. This makes moſt men as inſenſible of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, as <hi>Senecaes</hi> foole <hi>Harpaſtes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Senecats.</note> of her naturall blindneſſe: Shee knew (ſaith hee) that ſhee was blind, and yet ſhee often intreated her guide to lead her out of doores, becauſe the houſe was darke. It is even ſo with moſt men; I may too juſtly make <hi>Seneca's</hi> Application; <hi>Rem incredibilem narro, ſed veram;</hi> I tell you a very ſtrange, but a true tale: Men are ſuch ſtrangers to themſelves, and ſins; if you charge them with any, They will ſay, and ſweare, and binde it with a curſe, They know it not; In the very ſame termes that <hi>Peter</hi> deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Maſter, <hi>Non novi hominem,</hi> I know not the man. But when
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:13936:80"/> Chriſt lookes backe once, then <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> weepes bitterly. When men finde themſelves narrowly eyed and obſerved by him, that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually looks downe from heaven <note place="margin">Pſal. 14.</note> upon the children of men, to ſee if there be any, that will underſtand and ſeeke after God; then they come crouching into the Temple with all humilitie as did this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican. Who firſt, ſtood a farre off. Secondly, preſumed not ſo much as to lift up his eyes to heaven Thirdly, ſmote his hand upon his breaſt, which was the laſt poſture.</p>
            <p>This ſmiting his hand upon his breaſt, as it argued aboundance of humilitie, ſo it expreſſed aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſignificancie. He ſmote his breaſt, ſometime the cave and dungeon of a wilfull, ſlaviſh, and a rebellious heart; from whence, as from an impure fountaine, iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed evill thoughts, adulteries, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, fornications, thefts, ſlanders, and all the noiſome luſts that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file the man: but now the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of a broken heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:13936:80"/> ſpirit, groaning under the former burden of bondage and captivitie, and deſiring to breake up priſon with all the violence the hand can aſſiſt it with. Such are the paſſions and diſtractions of troubled and perplexed conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that as when a tree is torne up by the rootes, it leaves the ground all rent &amp; mangled where it ſtood; ſo when ſinne is newly rooted out of the heart with much violence, it leaves it much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and perplexed; commanding the hand as ſtrickt a ſervice as <hi>Theſeus</hi> did <hi>Hercules,</hi> that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <note place="margin">Sen. Trag.</note> an unnaturall murder up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his wife and children; <hi>Percute, percute ictu valido; non enim debent mollite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r tractari ea pectora, quae tanti ſceleris conſcia extitêrunt.</hi> Strike, and ſtrike valiantly; for ſuch corrupt hearts, or breaſts as theſe, ought not to be favoured, that are guiltie of ſuch outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and abominable wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>But to draw towards a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the firſt part, which is the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:13936:81"/> manner of the Publicans devotion. Without queſtion theſe three po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of his; a mannerly diſtance in the Temple, ſtanding a farre off; dejection of the countenance, not prefuming ſo much as to lift up his eyes to heaven; and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his hand upon his breſt, muſt needs bee true ſignes of hearty hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, if heartily performed. But let mee give you this Caveat by the way: whoſoever hee bee, that ſhall ſo eagerly affect the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ceremony, as not principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to intend the inward ſincerity, the <hi>non ſum ſicut caeteri</hi> will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſteale upon that man, and an arrogant conceipt of proud humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity (as was formerly premiſed) even in theſe commendable ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures will ſpoile all the ſervice.</p>
            <p>For example ſake: The Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites. <hi>Ion.</hi> 3. Proclaimed a faſt, and <note place="margin">Ion. 3.</note> put on Sackecloth, from the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt even to the leaſt of them; and God was ſo well pleaſed with it, that hee repented him of the evill, that hee ſaid, hee would doe unto
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:13936:81"/> them, and he did it not. The Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites againe, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58. they fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Iſal. 58.</note> as hardly, and went as courſely as ever the Ninivites did; and yet God was ſo infinitely diſpleaſed with them, that he ſleighted, and altogether neglected their ſervice; whereupon they exclaime, and cry out hand-ſmoothe upon him: <hi>Wherefore have wee faſted, and thou ſeeſt it not? And puniſhed our ſelves, and thou regardeſt it not?</hi> The Holy Ghoſt gives a reaſon of both, in both places. God ſaw the Ninevites workes, but he ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſhewes in the Iſraelites: The one turned from their evill wayes, the other followed their owne inventions: The one faſted from ſinne as well as from food, Every man turned from his evill way (ſaith the text) and from the wickedneſſe that was in his hands: the other, when they faſted from food, feaſted on ſinne, whereupon the Lord by his Prophet moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them: Is this the faſt that I have have choſen, that a man
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:13936:82"/> ſhould afflict his ſoule for a day, or hang downe his head like a Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh, or lye downe in Sackecloth and aſhes? Wilt thou call this an acceptable faſt unto the Lord? Is not this rather the faſt that I have choſen, to looſe the bands of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, to take off the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that yee breake eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yoake? Is it not to deale thy bread unto the hungry, and that thou bring the poore that wander, into thine houſe; when thou ſeeſt the naked that thou clothe him, and lude not thy ſelfe from thine owne fleſh? It ſeemes it is not the emptineſſe of the craw, nor the roughneſſe of the garment, nor the tumbling in aſhes, which are but outward ſignes of an inward <note place="margin">Maro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſignia. Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> cauſe, rather <hi>paſſiones quàm opera</hi> (as one truely terms them) paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then actions, not ſought, or affected, or ſtuddied for, but ſuch as in ſorrow, or feare, or ſome ſuch like perturbations, offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and are conſequent of their
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:13936:82"/> owne accords, as helpes to expreſſe unto the world, our inward diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions. I ſay none of all theſe ſimply conſidered in themſelves can give any pleaſure or content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Almighty, but the unfained ſorrow of the heart, and the true humility of the minde, which theſe outward humiliations of the body give ſome aſſurance and teſtimony of.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe ſtood the caſe with the Sacrifices of the old Law: <hi>Nunquam in odoribus Sacrificiorum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>delectatus eſt dominus, niſi in ſide &amp; deſiderio offerentis.</hi> The ſenſible and ceremoniall handling of theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, without the inward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the heart, with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did but ſignifie, was never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted or approoved of God. Without this, how abhominable was the outward countenance, or lineaments of the Iſraelites ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. Their Rammes, their <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ai. 1.</note> fed Beaſts, their Bullockes, their Lambes, their Goates, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, their Sabbaths, their new
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:13936:83"/> Moones, their Feſtivals. Alas the Searcher of all hearts knew, this was but the dead carkaſſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion without the quickning ſpirit, and therefore he proteſteth that he will have nothing to doe with them; hee is full, and over-full; they are loathſome, and burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and abhominable unto him.</p>
            <p>How much more boldly then may I aſſirme of our ſacrifices of Chriſtianity under the Goſpell, or indeed but the very huskes of them, without a faithfull and humble heart, which is their <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah,</hi> and Captaine to goe in and out before them, I may either ſpeake mildly with <hi>Origen,</hi> they <note place="margin">Origen.</note> are but <hi>nutus tantum &amp; opus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> bare ceremony and dumbe ſhew, they have neither ſpeech nor language: For certainely the crouching of the body, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the countenance, or the knocking of the breſt, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodily exerciſe, either with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or without the Temple, of it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:13936:83"/> profiteth nothing, unleſſe the inward operation of the ſpirit give life to quicken it. Or to ſpeake ſome thing more tartly with <hi>Lactantius;</hi> They are not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices <note place="margin">Lact.</note> but ſacriledges, robbing God of the better part, and as <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi> ſtiles the idle repetitions of the Iewes, The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord, this is the Temple of the Lord, <hi>Verba mendaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Lying words; ſo may I theſe, <hi>Opera mendacil,</hi> Lying workes: or of leſſe ſubſtance yet; <hi>Vmbrae mendacii,</hi> Lying ſhaddowes, ſo fraudulently handled, and ſo hypocritically diſſembled, as if men went about to lye unto the Holy Ghoſt, and to cheate (if it were poſſible) the Searcher of all hearts.</p>
            <p>Would you know then how the Publicans poſtures may ſafely be performed in the Temple, with a good conſcience to the Servitor, and a commendable grace unto ſervice, that all things may be done decently, and in order; then briefly
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:13936:84"/> thus. The Philoſopher compares the heart of man ſeated in the middeſt of the body to a Princely Monarch, in the middeſt of his kingdome ſitting in his chaire of State, commanding as his ſubjects every facultie of the minde, and every member of the body to doe him ſervice; ſaying, to the foot goe, and it goeth; to the tongue ſpeake this, and it ſpeaks it; to the hand doe this, and it doth it. Now you know it is lawfull and juſt, that the King ſhould command the ſubject, but no reaſon or conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that the ſubject ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the King. Whatſoever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable poſtures then are perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the privitie of the heart, they are lawfully warranted by the King, and they are thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy: But if either the body ſhall bowe, or the head droope, or the hand ſmite, and not the heart conſent; ſuch poſtures as theſe muſt needs be prepoſterous, altogether irregular, and hypocriticall, and whoſoever ſhall looke for thanks
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:13936:84"/> or recompence for ſuch fancies as theſe, he doth but delude himſelfe as the Prophets dreamer did, who ate by imagination at mid-night, and when hee awoke from ſleepe, his ſoule had nothing.</p>
            <p>Let every member of the body then, and every facultie of the minde be ſo ſubject to the higher powers of the heart, that as the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivites preſumed not to venter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Generall humiliation, without lawfull authoritie from the King and the Councell; ſo let neither the body bowe, nor the head droope, nor the hand ſmite, without a lawfull <hi>Fiat</hi> from the heart and affections; So bee it. Then ſhall I be ſure both to ſeeme as I am, and to be as I ſeeme; Not to be <hi>intùs Nero, foris Cato, totus ambiguus, Monſtrum;</hi> A Saint with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and a Divell within, an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite in both, a meere monſter: But like unto <hi>Nathauael</hi> a true Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, in whoſe heart, and hand, and tongue there is no guile. So then (to conclude the point in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:13936:85"/> language) When I come into the Temple to doe my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervice, I will bowe my heart to the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and I will bowe my body alſo, for he is the Creator of that too: My heart ſhall droope firſt, and my head ſhall droope next: firſt my heart ſhall bleed, and then my hand ſhall ſmite, and ſo ſhall I be ſure mine Organs are in tune, and I may begin my ſervice when I pleaſe. And ſo I paſſe from the Organ, to the Quire; from the pipe, to the voyce; from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, to the Song: <hi>Deus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitius eſto mihi peccatori.</hi> O God, be mercifull to mee a ſinner.</p>
            <p>Wee are now come unto the ſong it ſelfe, you ſee; ready prickt unto our hands, by the hand and heart of humilitie it ſelfe, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent artiſt in his kinde, the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Publican. The firſt note hee reaches is a note above <hi>Ela,</hi> no lower then the higheſt, <hi>Oh God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God then (it ſeemes) is the firſt note hee reaches, and higher he
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:13936:85"/> cannot reach, neither for name, nor puritie, nor glory. Hee is a tranſcendent note above all notes for name: They ſhall know (ſaith <hi>David)</hi> that thou, whoſe name is Iehovah, art the moſt high God over all the earth. Hee is ſuch a tranſcendent note of puritie, that the Moone ſhines not, and the Starres are impure in his ſight, and the Cherubims clap their wings <note place="margin">Eſa. 6. 3.</note> upon their faces, and cry continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; <hi>Holy, holy, holy, is the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And hee is ſuch a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cendent note of glory, that hee is <note place="margin">Pſal. 104. Pſal. 68. 13. Pſa. 50. 1.</note> become exceeding glorious (ſaith <hi>David)</hi> hee is clothed with Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and honour. Hee decks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with light as with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſpreads out the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens like a curtaine. The Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ots of this God are twentie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands even thouſands of Angels. This is the Lord even the moſt mightie God, that hath ſpoken and called the world, from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of the Sunne unto the going downe thereof. The glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:13936:86"/> of this God ſhall indure for ever. Bleſſed be his glorious name for ever, and let all the earth bee filled with his Majeſtie, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Diapaſon, that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to this high trebble, is a deep baſe. Deepe indeed, he reaches a note below <hi>Gam ut,</hi> baſer then the baſeſt, a ſinner. This Baſe was once a Meane, if hee could have kept himſelfe there. <hi>Minuiſti eum paulò ab Angelis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid)</hi> thou madeſt him a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to the Angels, an innocent and a ſpotleſſe man in his eſtate of integritie; but his voyce beeing crackt by over-reaching himſelfe, this <hi>homo</hi> became <hi>homulus,</hi> and ſo fell a note lower; and by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of errour, this <hi>homulus</hi> became <hi>mulus,</hi> a note lower yet, a beaſt and no man; a worme or vermine, and no beaſt; the baſeſt of all baſes, a Sinner. Now then for a judicious Artiſt to tel me juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how many Eights there may bee betwixt this high treble, and
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:13936:86"/> this deepe baſe; this mightie Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, and this ſilly worme; this fountaine of puritie and this ſinke of impietie; this glorious Majeſty, and this deſpectible miſery; this great God and this wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. There had need (you ſee) to bee two good cloſing parts to make the Muſicke ſweet and full betwixt theſe two extreame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames the trebble and the baſe, and ſo behold there is: A true Tenor to cloſe with the Baſe, that alwayes ſings <hi>Me</hi> in <hi>E la, Me</hi> to make the Muſicke full, by an humble and heartie confeſſion of ſinne, or elſe it could never be; And a ſweet Meane to cloſe with the Trebble, to make the Muſicke harmonious; by an humble and heartie apprecation of mercy. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, propitius eſto mihi peccatori,</hi> O God bee mercifull to mee a Sinner.</p>
            <p>This for the Diapaſons, now for the cloſing parts: And firſt I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you marke, how truly the Tenor cloſes with the Baſe. To
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:13936:87"/> bee a ſinner, and not to know it is the part of a bungler, <hi>Qui pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epicuru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſe neſcit, non vult corrigi,</hi> It was the beſt doctrine that ever Epicure preached. To bee a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and to know it, and not to acknowledge it, is the part of a fumbler; to ſlubber and ſhift a ſinne from the man to the woman, and from the woman to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, this is but muffling the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and juggling with God. But the skilfull and ingenuous Artiſt, will both know, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and rather aggravate then mince a ſinne: He will both produce, and accuſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne himſelfe, as <hi>Ionas</hi> to the Mariners, <hi>Novi Quia propter me</hi> (there is his mee in <hi>Ela me) Take</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ion. 1.</note> 
               <hi>mee, and caſt mee into the Sea; for I know that for my ſake this mightie ſtorme is come upon you. Deus, propitius eſto mihi peccatori:</hi> O God, be mercifull to mee a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. When the Tenor cloſes thus truly with the baſe, that makes the Muſicke full.</p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:13936:87"/>
            <p>So full indeed, that it even ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed all the Saints of God, they were never in quiet till they had learned this part. It was the part of <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Nathan; Peccavi,</hi> I <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12 2 Sam. 24</note> have ſinned. And againe to God himſelfe, both with a reſtriction to the perſon, and aggravation to the ſinne, <hi>Valdè peccavi,</hi> I have exceedingly ſinned. And, <hi>Ego ſum qui peccavi.</hi> And, <hi>Ego ſum qui inique egi;</hi> It is I, and only I that have done wickedly. The part of <note place="margin">Iob 7. 1 ſim. 1. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Iob, Peccavi,</hi> I have ſinned. And the part of the very chiefeſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to proclaime himſelfe the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chiefeſt Sinner; <hi>Ego peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum primus,</hi> I am the chiefeſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Let preſumptuous Phariſees then harpe upon an harſher ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, and ſay, God be mercifull to this, or that man, moſt odious, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſinners: God I thanke thee, I am not as theſe men are: But oh may it be my part, and oh may it bee all their parts, at the very laſt cloſe of our ſervice, and at the laſt blaſt that ſhall give
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:13936:88"/> breath unto the Organ; That breath, and pipe, and voyce, and all may humbly conclude with this Publican: <hi>Deus, propitius eſto mihi peccatori:</hi> O God, bee mercifull to mee a ſinner. This is the firſt cloſing part, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enor to the Baſe, and a true one too.</p>
            <p>In the next place I beſeech you, marke how ſweetly the Meane cloſes with the Treble. Mercy is the onely Meane to reach ſo high a Treble as God himſelfe is: If we reach at any other of his attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes wee over-reach our ſelves. If at his wiſdome, it confounds us; If at his glory it dazel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us; if at his Majeſtie, it beates us downe; if at his juſtice, it ſtrikes us dead; but if wee reach at mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, hee preſently cloſes with us; <hi>Miſericordiam vult, non ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> in this ſenſe too; Hee had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſave us by his mercy, then ſacrifice us by his juſtice. We can no ſooner looke homewards, and reſolve to returne to this Father of all mercies; but preſently like
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:13936:88"/> that over-joyed one in the Goſpel, he runnes halfe way to meete his Prodigals, hugges us in the armes of his mercie, falles upon our neekes and kiſſes us with the kiſſes of his mouth, brings us home to his houſe the Church, changes our garments of iniquitie, puts upon us the robe of our elder bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers righteouſneſſe, gives all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible entertainment, and cauſes his family to rejoyce with us; for that the dead are revived, and the loſt are found. This is the ſecond clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing part, the Meane to the Treble, and a ſweet one too.</p>
            <p>Now we have ſufficiently proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the notes, let us for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of all admire the ſingular skill of this Artiſt in ſetting and compoſing the Chords, that wee may the better relliſh the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Hee gives not the leaſt touch upon the merits of Saints or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of Angels; that Clift is too low to begin his Treble upon: ſo ſweet a meane as mercy, would never cloſe with the harſh, a Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:13936:89"/> as Saints or Angels. Neither preſumes hee to touch upon the ſtraine of his owne merits; that Clift is too high to begin his baſe upon. Neither thinkes hee it ſafe to touch upon a ſtraine of ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence; that Clift is too falſe to begin his Tenor upon: ſo deepe a baſe as a ſinner, and ſo falſe a Tenor as a merit-monger, would never cloſe. Neither dares hee touch upon the ſtraine of Gods juſtice: that Clift is too harſh to beginne his Meane upon: there would bee ſuch a jarring diſcord betwixt juſtice and miſery, they would never cloſe, but marre all the harmony. But when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins his ſervice upon the higheſt Treble, God; and miſery like a ſweet Meane cloſes with him. And concludes with the deepeſt baſe, a Sinner; and humble confeſſion like a true Tenor cloſes with him; then is the Muſicke ſweet and full, no matter how curious the eare be that heares it. <hi>Oratio humilian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſe, penetrat nubes;</hi> The prayer
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:13936:89"/> of him that humbleth himſelfe thus, goeth thorow the clouds, and ceaſeth not till it come neere, and will not depart till the higheſt of all have reſpect unto it. <hi>Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit miſeria, deſcendit miſericordia;</hi> Humble miſery creeps up, melting mercy drops downe. God, and man, and Artiſt, and hearers, and all are pleaſed. Heaven and earth, Men and Angels, Saints and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſtand all amazed, as raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at this harmony. <hi>Deus propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius eſto mihi peccatori:</hi> O God be mercifull to mee a ſinner. And thus ends the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans ſervice with the time, and mine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:90"/>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:13936:90"/>
            <head>THE SIXTH SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Luke 18. 14.</bibl>
               <q>I tell you this man went downe to his houſe juſtified rather then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for every one that exalteth himſelfe ſhall bee abaſed; and hee that humbleth himſelfe ſhall bee exalted.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS one verſe clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes up the <hi>ſeries</hi> of the whole Parable, and comprehends the two laſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals we obſerved in it, when wee firſt ventured on it: The Event,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:13936:91"/> and the Application. You have already heard the occaſion, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced our bleſſed Saviour to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it, which was a diſcoverie of three groſſe corruptions in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his auditours. The firſt was a preſumptuous ſelfe-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, by reaſon of a fond conceit of merit in their owne workes: They truſted in themſelves. The ſecond was an arrogant conceit of inherent righteouſneſſe, that they were juſt. The third was a moſt proud and uncharitable contempt and vilification of others.</p>
            <p>You have likewiſe heard of the particular paſſages of the Parable it ſelfe, and the ſeverall devotions of the two men, whom it princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concerned; the Phariſee, and the Publican. The Phariſee ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Eraſ. par.</note> next unto the propitiatorie, as moſt worthy in his owne eyes to ſtand Iig by Ioll, and diſcourſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly with his Maker, prayed by himſelfe thus: God I thanke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. I am not as other men are, that altogether live by wrong and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:13936:91"/> robberie, by ryot and luxurie, by odious defiling their neighbours bed, or by any ſcandalous or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull courſe of living, as doth this Publican; I pamper not my <hi>genius</hi> as other men doe, but I faſt twice in the weeke; and I rm ſo far from doing the leaſt wrong to any, that I defraud not the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of his leaſt dues: for I give tithes of all that I poſſeſſe. This was the ſwelling Oration of the Phariſee, froathing and foaming like the Sea at full; which happily in it ſelfe might be true, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly thanke-worthy, becauſe he thanked his God for it: but his God thankes not him for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee onely praiſed himſelfe, and condemned his brother. But the Publican, as a moſt wretched and dejected caitife, onely diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with himſelfe, by reaſon of the guilt of ſinne and gall of conſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſtood trembling a farre off, ſo miſerably aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in himſelfe, that he would not ſo much as lift up his eies to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:13936:92"/> heaven, but ſmote his breſt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>O God, be mercifull to me a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> The Phariſee came onely to give thankes for his goodneſſe, without either inward feeling of the want of grace, or outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſinne; though the very heart of his devotion was moſt miſerably tainted and infected with it, by an arrogant advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his owne worthineſſe, and a raſh accuſation of his brothers weakeneſſe. But the Publican puts all the good that ever hee did into the hinder part of the wallet, and onely layes before him, cloſe unto his conſcience, the evill hee had done; ſmites his breſt as the only fountaine of his impure thoughts, but impurer actions; and though hee preſumes not ſo much as to lift up his eies to heaven, yet hee only calls unto the God of heaven for mercy for both. <hi>Deus, propitius eſto mihi peccatori.</hi> O God, bee mercifull to me a Sinner.</p>
            <p>And would you now know the Event of all this? then reade the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:13936:92"/> former part of this Text, and you ſhall finde, that <hi>iſte remotus &amp; cum contemptu,</hi> that reſpued contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Publican, in the Phariſees eye, to become <hi>Hic vir, &amp; Deo proximus,</hi> the only man of account in Gods eye. That poore crippled Sinner, that came crawling into the Temple, even bowed quite double by his infirmitie, is ſent home to his houſe juſtified for a ſtraight and an upright man, ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and leaping, and prayſing God. But the Phariſee, the I, <hi>per ſe I,</hi> or the <hi>Ipſe Ego</hi> in his owne eyes, is quite caſt out of the ſight of God, excommunicated the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Saints, and ſent home to his owne peſt-houſe an infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous leaper as white as ſnowe. This man went home to his houſe juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied rather then (or, and not) the other.</p>
            <p>Againe, would you know the Application of all this? then reade the latter part of the Text, and you ſhall finde, that theſe things were written for our learning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction;
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:13936:93"/> that wee through pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope. For this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was propounded not onely in <hi>terrorem populi</hi> (as was promiſed in the Preface) for the terrour and confuſion of hollow hypocrites, (as places of execution are ſet up on hills, or hie wayes, to terrifie the like offenders) but alſo in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolationem ſanctorum,</hi> for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation of true Saints. And therefore <hi>legehiſtoriam, nè fias hiſtoria;</hi> Read this Parable, leſt thou be made a parable. Reade the effect of it to thy profit, leſt thou feele the Event of it to thy puniſhment: For He that firſt propounded it to ſome, applyes it now to all: yet ſo, that as hee would have all in generall to note it; ſo hee would have every one in particular to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it. For this purpoſe, like that good Shepheard, he ſhews us both <hi>virgam &amp; baculum,</hi> both, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us; hee hath a rod to beate downe our pride, hee hath a ſtaffe to raiſe up our humilitie. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:13936:93"/> that exalts himſelfe ſhall bee abaſed; but hee that humbleth himſelfe ſhall be exalted.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, would you know how to beleeve all this? why here is more then <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>dixit Ariſtotel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s:</hi> Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe averres it; the Truth it ſelfe ſpeakes it; the eternall Word himſelfe hath given the word, and his teſtimonie muſt needes bee true: <hi>I ſay unto you.</hi> Hee that juſtified the ungodly, juſtified the Publican, and filled his hungry ſoule with good things; and he that alwaies reſiſteth the proud, ſent home the rich Phariſee empty away. He that did it ſpake it, and hee that ſpake it did it; the Event then muſt needes be true.</p>
            <p>And for the Application wee may well demande with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who ſo able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the doctrine as the great Doctor himſelfe, who is both Doctor and doctrine too? who ſo able to confect and adminiſter the potion, as the great Phyſician
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:13936:94"/> himſelfe, that is both Phyſician and Phyſicke too? Hee that is the Subject of all Text, read unto his auditours this Text; Hee that ſpake as never man ſpake, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and delivered unto them this Parable: And He that is the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall High-Prieſt, and Biſhop of all our ſoules, hath framed both for them and us, this uſefull applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That every one that exalteth himſelfe ſhall bee abaſed, but hee that humbleth himſelfe ſhall bee exalted. Reſt we then fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <note place="margin">Rev. 19.</note> and ſay with that beloved Diſciple, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. Theſe words of God are true, upon the authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke warrant of an <hi>Ipſe dixit,</hi> It was Chriſt himſelfe that ſpake it, it was Chriſt himſelfe that did it.</p>
            <p>So that now (wee ſee) the two laſt generalls of the whole Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are become the two conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable particulars of this Text: the former, preſents unto us the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent; the latter, the Application. The Event is this: The humble
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:13936:94"/> Publican, that ſtood trembling a farre off, not preſuming ſo much as to lift up his eies to heaven, but ſmiting his breaſt and crying, <hi>O God, be mercifull to mee a Sinner,</hi> is juſtified by our bleſſed Saviour; and not the arrogant and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Phariſee, that was perched up to the higheſt place in the Temple, not praying to his God, but prating to himſelfe, advancing himſelfe, and vilifying his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Phariſee that juſtified himſelfe is condemned, and the Publican that condemned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is juſtified. <hi>This man, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Videte fratres; magis placuit hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>in malis factis, quam ſuperbia in honis fact is.</hi> And indeed it is right worthy our note and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; that of the twaine, the Publican, that was humbled for his weakeneſſe, was juſtified ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Phariſee, that boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of his worthineſſe. The waies of God (it ſeemes) are not as mans waies, nor his thoughts as mans thoughts; He neither judges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:13936:95"/> to the outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, nor yet iuſtifies according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olineſſe:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non vox, ſed votum, non muſica chordula, ſed cor;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non clamans, ſed amans cantat in aure Dei.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>It is neither our great words, nor good workes, nor high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of either, that ſtrike any ſtroke at all in the act of juſtification before God. Not great words; for how many ſhall meete our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the cloudes at the laſt day with theſe ſwelling words: Lord, <note place="margin">Matth. 7. 22.</note> Lord, have wee not in thy Name propheſied, and by thy Name caſt out Devils, and by thy Name done many great miracles? but He ſhall ſhall ſhake them off with a <hi>Non novi vos,</hi> I never knew you. Not good workes: for righteous <hi>Abraham</hi> was juſtified by faith onely. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies that his faith was onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted unto him for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:13936:95"/> onely we are bold to enter into his ſecret chamber; where he deſires to enjoy the companie of his Spouſe by faith alone. It is not fit that any of the family of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhould ruſh in, to interrupt their privacie. But afterwards, when the doore is opened, and the Bridegroome come forth with his Bride into the waiting roome, to preſent her unto men and Angels all faire, and without ſpot; then (in the name of God) let all the ſervants and hand-maides attend. Then may wee give all diligence to adde unto our Faith Vertue; and to Vertue Knowledge; and to Knowledge Temperance; and to Temperance Patience; and to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience Godlineſſe; and to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Brotherly kindneſſe; and to Brotherly kindneſſe Love. For, if theſe things bee in us and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, they will make us that we ſhall neither bee barren nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Though Faith <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1. 5.</note> then bee <hi>Sola,</hi> alone; yet ſhe is not
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:13936:96"/> 
               <hi>ſolitaria,</hi> but gloriouſly attended by a whole guard of g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aces. As the eye in regard of its beeing, is not alone from the head; but in reſpect of ſeeing, it is alone: it is the eye onely in the head that ſees: So a true and lively Faith cannot poſſibly ſubſiſt without a whole traine of graces.</p>
            <p>What ſhall wee ſay then to this controverſie (to ſpeake in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles language.) Doe we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make voide the Law through Faith? God forbid; yea, wee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh the Law. Doe wee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make voide good workes through Faith? God forbid; yea, wee eſtabliſh good workes. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wee ſay, it were no way of preferment for the hand-maid ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take the wall of her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris; or to goe equall with her. If <hi>Bilhah</hi> ſupply the defects of <hi>Rachel,</hi> and beare children unto <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> let her remember notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that <hi>Rachel</hi> is above her, and ſingular in ſome reſpect. If <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be mounted into the ſecond Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:13936:96"/> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and become the next man unto the King; let him then eſpecially remember that the King hath reſerved the Throne unto himſelfe. Wee conceive (and we know wee ſtand upon a ſure ground) that wee can doe good workes no better right, then to to aſſigne them <hi>locum proprium,</hi> their owne place; to advance them higher, is but to bring them low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. The principall aime and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our bleſſed Saviour in the propoſition of this parable, was the conviction of certaine arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant and hypocriticall merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, truſting in the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of their owne workes, that they were juſt, and deſpiſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And after a plaine demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the controverſie, in the ſeverall paſſages of the parable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Temple by the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall devotions of the two men, the Phariſee and the Publican; the Event of all proclaimes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverfie ended in the Conſiſtorie; where the impartiall Iudge, that
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:13936:97"/> cannot lye, neither for feare nor fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, is pleaſed to pronounce this irrevocable ſentence. <hi>I ſay unto you, this man</hi> (that is, the humble Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, that renounced his own merits and layed hold by faith onely on Gods mercies) <hi>was juſtiſied rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other</hi> (that is the proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee) boaſting, and truſting to the broken ſtaffe of ſelfe-confidence.</p>
            <p>From whence I briefely gather thus much to conclude the point. That if ſuch dejected, and rejected humilitie, ſo over-clogged and preſſed downe with a maſſe of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, did, in the eſtimation of the Almightie, ſo tryumph and inſult over phariſaicall ſanctitie; how much more ſhall the ſame hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, ſupported by true pietie, become more then a conquereſſe through him that ſo infinitely loves her? And if pride and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie bee ſo miſchievous to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a whole broode of vertues; oh, what a generation of Vipers is ſhee able to hatch in a neaſt of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? If our bleſſed Saviour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:13936:97"/> thoſe, that boaſt of the good works they havedone, whereof they may ſeeme to have ſome ſmall ſhare, becauſe both by Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting, accompanying, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummating grace, they do in ſome <note place="margin">Gratia praeveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitans, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummans.</note> ſort co-operate with God; (ſuch as are faſting, praying, giving of almes, paying of tithes, &amp; the like) and give not God all the glory in them, and for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; how much more ſhall he condemne thoſe that boaſt of their good qualities, and comely features, wherein they have no ſhare at all, and yet rob God of all his glory for them; (ſuch as are health, beautie, comelines, ſtrength and agilitie of body, and the like:) certainely moſt abominable muſt theſe fooles needs be in the ſight of God. It is a ſufficient warning gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us by the Prophet. <hi>Let not the rich man glory in his riches, nor the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrong man glory in his ſtrenth, nor the wiſe man glory in his wiſdome; but let him that glorieth glory in this, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> knowes, and underſtands me, ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord.</hi> Whereupon the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:13936:98"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> moſt humbly reſolves upon an, <hi>Abſit gloriari. God forbid that I ſhould glory in any thing, but in the Croſſe of Chriſt, whereby the world is crucified to me, &amp; I unto the world.</hi> All other glory is but vaine, and will end in ſhame. The Event of this Parable hath already prooved it fatal to others; &amp; (if we take not the more heede) the enſuing appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation will proove it fearefull to our ſelves. <hi>For every one that exalts himſelfe ſhall be abaſed; but he that humbleth himſelfe ſhall bee exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am ſecuris ad radicem:</hi> Now is the axe layed unto the roote of the tree by the beſt Worke-man that ever ſtroke ſtroake: Every tree ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that brings not forth good fruit now, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire. The uſe and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the doctrine is framed by the beſt Preacher that ever was, or ſhall be; He therefore that hath eares to heare, let him now heare hearing beleeve, and beleeving practiſe the things that belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his peace, leſt hereafter they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:13936:98"/> kept for ever from his eares: At firſt indeed the Parable was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded but to ſome, but the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and application was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto all. And indeed no more then needs; for every man by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is like <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiting himſelfe to be ſome great man. We have all by nature a kind of an inbred Pope, a phantaſticall opinion of our owne works: <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſus</hi>-like we doat upon our owne ſhadows, though we finde no reall vertue, or true ſubſtance in us. And this is no better then the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry head of the Serpent, as <hi>Luther</hi> tearmes it: <hi>Omnium in juſtitiarum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit: de praſump.</note> 
               <hi>ferè ſola cauſa eſt juſtitia.</hi> An arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant preſumption of our owne righteouſneſſe, is the onely cauſe almoſt, of all unrighteouſneſſe. But ſo great a thing is it for a man to ſeeme ſmall in his owne eyes, that no man is able to learne that leſſon of any man, but of him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who being in the forme of God, and thought it no robberie to be equal with God, tooke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:13936:99"/> him the forme of a Servan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and became man; yea the very ſcorne of men, and the contempt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. It is high time then for the ſeede of the woman to breake this Serpents head; and for that great Actor and teacher of humilitie to read unto us a large Lecture of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie in his owne perſon: not onely by propounding a ſpeciall Parable to ſome, but by framing a generall doctrine to all, and a particular application to every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall. So that now the caſe ſtands not onely betweene the Phariſee and the Publican; but <hi>Every one that exalts himſelfe ſhall be abaſed; and every one that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles himſelfe ſhall be exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee then the finger of the Application directly points at the fall of pride, and the reſurrection of humilitie. Every mountaine and hill ſhall be brought low, but every valley ſhall be exalted. Pride and humilitie bee the two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Roades, that are moſt tracked and beaten in this mortall pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage;
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:13936:99"/> the one leades to miſerie, the other to glory. The former of theſe is chalked outby <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 16.</note> 16. <hi>Pride goeth before deſtruction, and an haughty ſpirit before a fall.</hi> The firſt that found out this road was <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that rode poſte from heaven to hell. The ſecond was <hi>Adam,</hi> that poſted from Paradiſe to miſerie. The third was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoaſt, that poſted from the pompe and pleaſures of <hi>Egypt</hi> to a fearefull ruine in the red Sea. And preſently that roade grew ſo common, one paſſenger could not paſſe for another; for not onely <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram, Saul, Abſolon, Adonias, Rehoboam, Senacherib, Nebuchadnezzar, Antiochus,</hi> and divers others haue made the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Story blacke with fearefull preſidents of ruine; but daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples doe continually proove it a fatall thorow-faire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>The latter of theſe was chalked out by <hi>Solomon</hi> too. <hi>Proverbs</hi> 15. <note place="margin">Prov. 15.</note> Where hee tells us, That humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:13936:100"/> is the high-way to glory. But (I muſt needes ſay) this roade was firſt found out by a greater then <hi>Salomon,</hi> even the propounder and applyer of this Parable, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Author and finiſher of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie it ſelfe; who poſted ſo faſt from heaven to earth, leaping upon the mountaines, and skipping upon the hills, to make plaine this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trodden path of humilitie; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee opened unto us the gate of glory, by his owne firſt entrance with the Apoſtles <hi>Propter quod,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil 2.</note> wherefore God hath highly exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. The next that poſted in this roade after him, was the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> his Mother; who by reaſon of her extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary lowlineſſe, was ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily magnified, that all ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding generations ſhall call her bleſſed. The next after her was <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt;</hi> in whom becauſe our Saviour found <hi>Omnia vocalia,</hi> (as one divinely notes) his words, his thoughts, his deeds, his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his diet, his life, his death,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:13936:100"/> to be ſo many preaching voices, and vocall Preachers to humble penance: therefore our Saviour dignifies him, <hi>Matthew</hi> 11. with <note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> the name of a Prophet, and more then a Prophet; for amongſt them that are begotten of women, there aroſe not a greater then <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt.</hi> Yea even hollow-hearted <hi>Achab,</hi> loſt not a ſufficient reward for his hypocriticall humiliation: wherefore the Lord promiſed, <note place="margin">1 King. 21 25.</note> That he would not bring the evill upon him in his dayes. Much more the poore widow, that drops in but <hi>duo minuta,</hi> two mites into Gods treaſury, out of her true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted humilitie, and humble penurie, ſhall bee more accepted with God, then a whole world of vaine-glorious hypocrites, that caſt in never ſo many thouſand talents, out of their proud arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, and arrogant ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie.</p>
            <p>So that this may ſtand for the maine pillar of the Application: That according to our proportion
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:13936:101"/> of humilitie, God will bee ſure to prepare us a portion of glory: And according to our proportion of pride, hee will bee as ſure to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare us a portion of vengeance. Our bleſſed Saviour tells us, <hi>That in his Fathers houſe there are many Manſions.</hi> Speaking of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that cannot be ſhaken: that habitation that is everlaſting: that inheritance that is immortall, and undefiled, and fades not away: that houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heavens. And why ſo many Manſions in this houſe? but onely to aſſure us of divers degrees of glory there, for divers degrees of humilitie heere. <hi>As there is one glory of the Sunne,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> 
               <hi>and another glory of the Moone, and another glory of the Starres, one Starre differing from another in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; ſo ſhall it likewiſe bee in the reſurrection of the dead.</hi> That Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met that appeares moſt dull, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-clouded by true humilitie in this Sublunary firmament, ſhall ſhine the brighteſt Starre in that
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:13936:101"/> Empyreall and Imperiall Orbe. And that vaine-glorious Meteor, that gives the greateſt flaſh in this lower Region, ſhall ſinke yet low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to that infernall Legion. For looke how much that glittering Whore. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. hath glorified <note place="margin">Rev. 18.</note> her ſelfe, and lived in pleaſure heere; ſo much ſhall bee added to her torment and ſorrow here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>So that now (mee thinks) our bleſſed Saviour by the application of this Parable, ſpeaks the ſame in effect to us, that <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Iſraelites, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. I call heaven <note place="margin">Deut. 30.</note> and earth to record, that I have ſet before you this day life and death, good and evill, the broad way and common roade that leads unto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and the narrow way that leads unto life, though few there be that finde it. If you poſte on the roade of pride without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare or wit, you runne head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long downe into hell, and without a ſpeedy retentive there can bee no hope of you. But if you pace
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:13936:102"/> never ſo gently in the roade of humilitie, you are in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to heaven, and there is great joy of you, even amongſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of heaven. Every one that exalts himſelfe ſhall be abaſed: but every one that humbleth himſelfe ſhall be exalted.</p>
            <p>Not hee that is exalted by an other, either immediately by the God of heaven, or mediately by the King &amp; his Magiſtrates, which are gods on earth; ſuch exaltations as theſe, being humbly uſed, prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate no ruines. Nor hee that is humbled by an other; either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by God for a time, and preſently to returne to his former obſtinacy, as <hi>Pharaoh, Iulian, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> and the like; againſt whom the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> moſt juſtly, <hi>Percuſſiſti eos (Domine) &amp; non doluêrunt,</hi> Thou haſt ſmitten them (O Lord) and they have not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 3.</note> thou haſt conſumed them, but they have refuſed to receive correction: they have made their faces harder then a rocke: they
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:13936:102"/> have refuſed to returne. Or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by the Magiſtrare, that <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> beareth not the ſword in vaine, for he is the Miniſter of God to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute vengeance on them that doe evill. And therefore ſuch humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liations as theſe prognoſticate no riſings. But he that humbles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; not in outward hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but inward ſinceritie: for as in <hi>Platoes</hi> ſchoole, every mans ſoule is himſelfe; ſo in Chriſts Schoole, every mans heart is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. It is not then the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tongue, or the humble knee, or the humble habit, but the humble heart, that is next unto advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Lord, (ſaith <hi>David)</hi> I am not puft in minde, I doe not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe <note place="margin">Pſal. 131.</note> my ſelfe in great matters, that are too high for mee. But I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine my ſoule, and keepe it low, like as a child that is weaned from his mother; yea my ſoule is even as a weaned childe. A man that humbles himſelfe thus, when hee falles, hee riſes; and when hee is raiſed, he ſtands, as immooveable
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:13936:103"/> as Mount Sion, that ſtandeth faſt for ever. But hee that exaltes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hardens his heart, ſtiffens his necke, lifts up his countenance, and overlookes his equals, many times his betters, as if he would over-looke Cedars; Little (alas) doth this wretch dreame how neere his fall is; and that ſuch a fearefull one too, that will admit no riſing. When this man falles, <hi>mole ruit ſuâ,</hi> hee falles with ſuch a powder, that hee is even ground to powder; hee ſinkes from one miſery into another, from a flood of temporall, to a maine Ocean of eternall torment.</p>
            <p>Blame mee not then, if I lift up my voyce like a trumpet, and cloſe up both Parable, Event, and Application, and all pathetically with the Prophet. <hi>O earth, earth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 22.</note> 
               <hi>earth, heare the word of the Lord.</hi> Earth by creation, Earth by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, Earth by reſolution, looke but into thy firſt principles, thou cameſt earth, thou remaineſt earth, and thou returneſt earth.
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:13936:103"/> 
               <hi>O earth, earth, earth, heare the word of the Lord.</hi> Looke but into thy beſt thoughts, they periſh with thine earth; looke but upon thy freſheſt beautie, it fades before thine earth; looke but into thy ſoundeſt wiſedome, it ſavours of thine earth. <hi>O earth, earth, earth, &amp;c.</hi> Looke but above thee, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold an angry God of vengeance, that alwayes reſiſts proud earth; Looke but beneath thee, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold an ever-burning Tophet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared of old to torment proud earth; Looke but within thee, and behold a puddle and ſinke of ſinne that corrupts proud earth; Looke but againſt thee, and behold thine adverſary the divell, like a roaring Lion, alwayes ready at hand to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and condemne proud earth; Looke but round about thee, and behold many thouſands farre more deſerving, and yet farre more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble veſſels then thy ſelfe, of earth. And laſtly, looke but right before thee, and ſo looke once for all, and behold the Author and finiſher of
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:13936:104"/> thine earth; marke, and learne, what a ſingular precept and preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent hee reads unto thee, even in <hi>terrâ tuâ</hi> in thine owne earth. He, that was an eternall and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſed ſpirit, humbled himſelfe ſo low, as to ſtoope to a mortall and miſerable lump of thine earth; And in that earth he did <hi>infimum ſapere in altiſſimo</hi> clothe the higheſt majeſtie with loweſt miſery; And in that miſery, hee was <hi>liberrimus agens</hi> though <hi>miſerrimus patiens;</hi> hee was not humbled by an other, but <hi>quia ipſe voluit,</hi> hee humbled himſelfe; Neither was hee ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially, but ſubſtantially humble, and obediently humble, and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally obedient, and ſingularly le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> ſermon in <hi>Paſch.</hi>
               </note> even to a threefold <hi>uſque,</hi> the nature of man, the forme of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and the death of the croſſe: for theſe bee his ſteps of deſcent noted by the Apoſtle. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. <note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Humiliavit ipſe; &amp; Ipſe ſe; &amp; Ipſe obediens; &amp; obediens factus; &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus uſque.</hi> Hee was humbled; not by an other, but himſelfe; and his
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:13936:104"/> humilitie was obedient, and his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience legall, and his legalitie ſingular.</p>
            <p>Oh Earth, earth, earth, canſt thou behold humble God-man, cloathed in the ragged humilitie of thine earth, and thy ſelfe not clothed ſo much as with one ragge of the glorious humilitie of that God? canſt thou for ſhame en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſo miſerable a Soleciſme as <hi>humilem Deum &amp; ſuperbum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> an humble God of heaven, and a proud man of earth? wert thou any thing elſe but earth, thou wouldſt never ſpread it ſo proudly upon the face of the earth, <hi>terra oalcans terram,</hi> as if the earth ſhould never ſet her foote upon thy face. Cannot the bitter paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy Saviour, that ſplit the very ſtones, peirce thine earth? or his powerfull reſurrection that raiſed ſo many dead, quicken thy <note place="margin">This Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was preached the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day after Eaſter.</note> living earth? Conſider, oh conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what a Trophee it were to procure ſolemnitie to the inſtant ſeaſon; for that ugly and infernall
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:13936:105"/> feind pride, to be conjured downe to the divell in hell that firſt ſent her, never to riſe againe within this circle; and that faire damſell humilitie to bee raiſed (by virtue of a <hi>Tabitha Cumi)</hi> with her bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, that firſt found her, never to become a ſtranger more unto us; but that every Eaſter ſhee may ſpring a freſh, and bud out of the earth with that Prim-roſe of <hi>Sharon,</hi> and Lillie of the vallies; that no longer proud but humble earth may bee our Epithite. That beeing at this inſtant raiſed (with our bleſſed Saviour) from pride to humilitie, we may be hereafter rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with him from humilitie to glory. Which hee for his tender mercy grant us, who by his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood ſo dearely bought us, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> the righteous; to whom, with the Father, and the bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be aſcribed as is moſt meete, all poſſible honor, glory, power, praiſe, might, majeſtie, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo tri-uni Gloria.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:13936:105"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Recenſui Librum hunc cui titulus</hi> (The mirror of pure Devotion, &amp;c.) <hi>in quo nihil reperio quò minùs cum utilitate pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licâ Imprimatur, modò intra quatuor menſes proximè ſequentes typis mandetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex aedi: Londin: <date>Nov. 3. 1634.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sa. Baker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
